<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christianissimus Christianandus, or, Reason for the reduction of France to a more Christian state in Europ[e]</title>
            <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52753</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N383</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14468</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08164297</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08164297</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41002</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52753)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41002)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1235:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christianissimus Christianandus, or, Reason for the reduction of France to a more Christian state in Europ[e]</title>
                  <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills, and are to be sold by Jonathan Edwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  Foreign relations --  1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41002:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Chriſtianiſſimus Chriſtianandus. OR, REASON FOR THE REDUCTION OF FRANCE To a More Chriſtian State IN EUROP.</p>
            <q>Odimus Accipitrem quia ſemper vivit in Armis.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Jonathan Edwin,</hi> at the <hi>Three Roſes</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41002:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41002:2"/>
            <head>Chriſtianiſſimus Chriſtianandus. OR, Reaſon for the Reduction of FRANCE to a more Chriſtian State in EUROP.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>Section I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Being an INTROD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CTION.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ertainly 'tis high time to think of making the Miniſters of <hi>France</hi> better Chriſtians, when 'tis appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent they have taken up the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the <hi>Common Enemy</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom:</hi> and make his <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes</hi> the Rules and the Meaſure of their Proceedings. <hi>Abſolute Power</hi> at Home, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Empire</hi> abroad, is their Aim as well as the <hi>Turks;</hi> and ſeeing that by their Actions all the Duties of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity are laid in the dirt, it were hard to determine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which of the Two <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> would obtain Faireſt Quarter, after an abſolute Conqueſt. <hi>For though</hi> France <hi>be Owner of the better Faith, yet the other keep Faith better;</hi> becauſe all Travellers tell us the <hi>Turk</hi> counts it Religion to keep Word and Promiſe.</p>
               <p>But (it ſeems) <hi>France</hi> may do any thing <hi>Regnande
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41002:3"/>
cauſâ,</hi> as we ſhall ſhew by and by, when we come to tell how little value is made of <hi>Promiſes, Obligations, Alliances,</hi> and the <hi>Sacraments.</hi> In theſe things they exceed the <hi>Grand Seignior:</hi> but in matter and extent of <hi>abſolute Dominion</hi> they are his Rivals, and aſpiring to foreſtal him in his deſign upon <hi>Europ,</hi> to become ſole Maſters of a <hi>Weſtern,</hi> as he is of the <hi>Eaſtern Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</hi> And why not? Why ſhould not <hi>Louis</hi> the <hi>14th</hi> have it now, as his Predeceſſor, <hi>Charlemain,</hi> had it heretofore? His great Miniſters and Officers both Civil and Military, ſay, They have ample Territories, and very populous, and a moſt numerous Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; as much Courage as their Anceſtors, together with the advantage of being trained up either to Actions of War, or Warlike Exerciſes: alſo the Situation of their Country, and the Opportunity they have by it to invade their Neighbours upon all Occaſions; the Fruitfulneſs and Riches of the Soil, the prodigious quantity of all ſorts of Commodities, Manufactures, and other wayes, with which they ſupply neighbouring Countries; And laſtly, the vaſt Revenues of their Kings, who governing of late without check or controul at home, are thereby the more able to oppreſs other States or Princes. They boaſt how <hi>Charles</hi> the Eighth frighted all other <hi>Potentates,</hi> by the ſurpriſing. Conqueſt of the Kingdom of <hi>Naples:</hi> How they contended with the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Family, when it had been rais'd on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain to a wondrous Grandeur, by the acceſſion of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Provinces, united in the perſon of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth; and that their King <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, had like to have carried from him the <hi>Imperial Crown,</hi> having to that end engaged ſeveral of the <hi>Electors:</hi> but they forget to tell us, that when he had miſs'd it, then to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41002:3"/>
be revenged on the <hi>Emperor,</hi> and the other <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> he was the firſt that taught the <hi>French</hi> Kings the <hi>moſt Chriſtian trick</hi> of making Leagues with the <hi>Turks;</hi> for ſo did he with the Great <hi>Solyman the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent,</hi> as you may read in my Lord <hi>Herbert</hi>'s Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth: and God proſper'd him accordingly: for though he had ſeveral times the <hi>Turks</hi> aſſiſtance to carry on his Reverigeful Deſigns, to the hazard of all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> yet at laſt he was forc't to yield to the victorious Arms of that Emperor <hi>Charles,</hi> who took him Priſoner, and made him buy his Peace at an extraordinary Rate. But yet his Son <hi>Henry</hi> the Second had better ſucceſs, and would have extended his Dominions very far, had he not been prevented by a ſuddain, unfortunate Death, as did alſo his Succeſſor, <hi>Henry</hi> the Third.</p>
               <p>Then came on his Succeſſor, <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, and of him they boaſt, that he ſubdued Monſters of Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at home, and afterwards revived that Monſtrous Deſign of graſping all abroad: that having made good his Title to the Crown by the Succeſs of his Arms, he bent all his thoughts upon a Project, vaſt in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of it, as extraordinary in the Nature of it, intending no leſs than to caſt <hi>Europ</hi> into a new Model, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all the Kingdoms and Common-wealths that were in his time, to a certain number, and to bring them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch bounds as he ſhould think fit to preſcribe to them; but to reſerve to himſelf a Portion ſo conſiderable, as to have enabled him, or at leaſt his Succeſſors, to grow up into that ſtate of Univerſal Monarch, which had been firſt imagined by his Predeceſſor <hi>Francis.</hi> To this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect he had made choice of his Generals, and other great Officers, furniſhed his Arcenals with mighty
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41002:4"/>
Stores of Arms, and collected prodigious Sums of Money into his Treaſury; and then all came to nothing by a ſuddain unexpected ſtroke, which was given him by the Hand of <hi>Ravalliac.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After him, his Son <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>13th,</hi> Father of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King, though, by reaſon of ſome Domeſtick broyls and Civil Wars, he was not at leiſure to carry on the Project of his Predeceſſors, by employing that way the great Armory and Wealth which his Father had provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; yet ſtill he had an Eye towards it; and <hi>Cardinal Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelieu,</hi> with the reſt of his Miniſters, finding that the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> was very near bringing all <hi>Germany</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their ſubjection, and after the Battle of <hi>Prague</hi> ſtood fair to carry away <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Empire</hi> (the Darling of <hi>France</hi>) they haſten'd, with what ſpeed they could, to put an end to Civil Diſſentions, and having got quiet at Home, they being then courted by diverſe <hi>Princes</hi> for Aſſiſtance and Protection againſt the Auſtrian Family, were glad of the Opportunity: reckoning, that under a ſhew of aſſiſting weak Princes, they might at length take occaſion to ſhare with them in their Principalities, and by that means vaſtly increaſe their own Power: And ſo they did ſubdue new Provinces, and conſiderable Towns in <hi>Spain, Italy, Germany,</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countreys;</hi> which at laſt made the Princes as jealous almoſt of him, as they had been before of the <hi>Auſtrian:</hi> So that to prevent far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſchief they were content to ſit down with their loſſes, rather than truſt their <hi>French Alliances</hi> any longer. Which occaſioned that great Treaty held at <hi>Munſter,</hi> which ended in a general Peace, <hi>An.</hi> 1648.</p>
               <p>Now before I proceed, give me leave, by the way, to make uſe of what is paſt in theſe few Obſervations, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, That had not <hi>France</hi> had a marvellous Wit, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41002:4"/>
and Fortune, it could never have born its Head above water in the midſt of ſo many Waves and Tempeſts of Diſcord and Rebellion, as were rais'd during the Reigns of thoſe <hi>Kings,</hi> and yet continue ſtill in a Condition after all, to maintain it ſelf, and bid fair alſo againſt its <hi>Auſtrian Rival</hi> for the Maſtery of a <hi>General Dominion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, That in all Ages, as ſoon as their Inteſtine troubles have been over, they have ſtill, out of a reſtleſs, warlike Humour, endeavour'd to incroach upon their Neighbours, and for enlarging their own Lordſhip, laid hold upon all opportunities to diſturb Mankind; and they could never yet ſet any bounds to their Ambition.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, That this Ambitious humour of theirs, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the greatneſs of their Power, would long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time have brought all <hi>Europ</hi> under Subjection, if their own Diviſions and private Quarrels had not from time to time put back their Deſigns for many years; or had not their greateſt Princes been cut off before they could have finiſhed their intended work.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, and laſtly, as a conſequence of the three former, That it was, and ever will be, the true Intereſt of all <hi>Princes</hi> to oppoſe the <hi>French</hi> Deſigns: or if they have at any time occaſion to uſe them againſt other Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, yet ſtill to remember, <hi>That no Oppreſſion is like theirs;</hi> and that they meditate it alwayes, even in the midſt of Friendſhip: and therefore that they are not to accept of their Aſſiſtance longer or further than meer neceſſity or publick utility requires it; but to caſt them off as ſoon as the danger is over; as it was practiſed in the Peace of <hi>Paſſaw;</hi> in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, and that of <hi>Munſter;</hi> in both which the <hi>French</hi> were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented of further Progreſs by the Jealouſie of their <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</hi> However, in all ſuch occaſions, they ever made
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41002:5"/>
acquiſitions, and came off with great advantages.</p>
               <p>In the Stories of ſuch glorious Pranks of their Princes, it is that the <hi>French Miniſters</hi> do pride and delight them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and to their Monarchs, when youthful, they propound them for imitation. To this end, it was the Care of <hi>Cardinal Mazarine,</hi> in the Minority of the King now regnant, to provide him an agreeable Tutor, that might form and fix in the mind of his Majeſty, the greateſt <hi>Idea's</hi> of Glory and Warlike Enterprizes. This was the Biſhop of <hi>Rodes</hi> his firſt Governor, who, as ſoon as his young Maſter came to underſtand Letters, inſtead of diverting him with <hi>Romances,</hi> entertain'd him in reading the Lives and Actions of the greateſt of his Predeceſſors; but above all, recommended to him the Story and Model of a great Prince, in the high Atchievements of his Grand-father, King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth; as may be ſeen in a Book of his, written to that purpoſe, which hath ſince been publiſhed.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Prince,</hi> as well by his own <hi>Genius,</hi> as by the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Succeſs of his firſt Undertakings, hath reliſhed ſuch Inſtructions, and hath ſolely propoſed to himſelf that Example for the Rule of his Actions. The Hiſtory of that Great King hath been his moſt ordinary Study. He hath, in imitation of him, taken care to accumulate a vaſt Treaſure, and ſetled a mighty Revenue, ſought for Allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces abroad, and ſucceſsively rais'd many moſt numerous Armies. It's evident therefore, That he acts upon the very ſame draughts; and that all we ſee at preſent are but the Old Projects of his Predeceſſors renew'd, and the Effects of thoſe Impreſſions which he hath ſuck't in with his Milk, Do but read the Book call'd the <hi>Memoirs</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>4th,</hi> with thoſe of the Preſident <hi>Jeannin,</hi> and of the Biſhop of <hi>Rodes;</hi> and then conclude, that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41002:5"/>
whatſoever his moſt Potent Grand-Father had conceived in his Imagination, this King intends to bring forth by the Power of his Armies; <hi>viz.</hi> A Wondrous Theatre of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian Glory,</hi> planted upon a Mountainous heap of <hi>Chriſtian Sculls,</hi> to amaze and terrifie Mankind into an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Slavery.</hi> For, as the deſire of Glory hath no bound, and in regard his Years and preſent Condition put him into a capacity to run a longer courſe than did <hi>Henry le Grand,</hi> ſo we cannot reaſonably expect other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than that he, who hath ſo often croſs'd the <hi>Rhine</hi> with his laſt Summer's Succeſſes, will alſo, when he hath over-run the <hi>Continent,</hi> croſs the <hi>Narrow Seas</hi> to make his Viſits.</p>
               <p>His Pen-men have taken a great deal of pains to nouriſh theſe Thoughts in him, and have no other ſtudy but to feed this Natural Humour of his Majeſty, and transfuſe it alſo into his Son the <hi>Daulphin,</hi> having wholy ſacrificed their Pens to infuſe it, and tickle that Native deſire of Glory, which they have diſcovered in them both. The great rewards that have been given them for it, are authentick markes of an acceptance of their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: and ſurely ſuch acknowledgements from a young High Spirit, that believeth himſelf to be in a poſture to execute all that pleaſeth him, and who hath drunk down this Maxim, <hi>That to take poſſeſſion by the Sword, any Title is ſufficient</hi> muſt needs be a dangerous fore-running Sentence upon all the reſt of Mankind, againſt whom his Miniſters ſhall perſwade him that he hath any thing to pretend. Which yet more clearly to make appear to Us, We only need read the printed Books not long ſince dedicated to him; among which is one that carries this Title, <hi>viz. The Juſt Pretences of the King of</hi> France <hi>to the Empire;</hi> which Book having laid down this for a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41002:6"/>
Ground, <hi>That the Dominions of Soveraign Princes have always been the Dominions and Conqueſts of their Eſtates: and that the Dominions and Conqueſts of Crowns can be neither alienated nor preſcribed,</hi> at length draws out theſe two Concluſions:</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>That the greateſt part of</hi> Germany <hi>is the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and ancient Inheritance of the</hi> French <hi>Princes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>That</hi> Charlemain <hi>did poſſeſs</hi> Germany, <hi>as King of</hi> France, <hi>and not as Emperour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What may not be drawn from ſuch kind of Aſſertions?</p>
               <q>—<hi>Nihil eſt quod credere de ſe Ambitio laudata nequit.........</hi>
               </q>
               <p>If theſe things be believ'd in <hi>France,</hi> what may not the Scribes of <hi>France</hi> perſuade their Maſter? May they not as well prove and perſuade him, <hi>That he wears the Titles of all other Princes within the Pomel of his Sword?</hi> If one may judge of what is to come by what is paſt, all <hi>Europ</hi> will have cauſe enough to ſtand upon their guard, and take the <hi>All'arm,</hi> to prevent the Machinations of the <hi>French</hi> Miniſtry, whoſe ſole buſineſs 'tis, To blow up the Glory of their Maſter to a mighty <hi>Bubble;</hi> and 'tis indeed no more but a <hi>Bubble</hi> which he gets; he is at the Expence, whilſt they collect for themſelves mighty For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes out of the Ruines of Mankind, and feed the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals</hi> and the other Great <hi>Military Commanders,</hi> with Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations of ſharing other Princes Principalities, and, as faſt as they can Conquer, to be all made Princes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:41002:6"/>
               <head>SECTION II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Shewing how far the French Miniſters receded from the known Rules of Juſtice in beginning this War.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HIſtories tell us, That the Heathens made it a main point of Conſcience, never to begin a War upon their Neighbours or others, till they had for it good <hi>Juſtifying Cauſes.</hi> Among them, for this Principle the <hi>Romans</hi> were moſt eminent; and therefore ſuch <hi>Cauſes</hi> they in their Language termed <hi>Principia;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Beginnings</hi> or <hi>Principles,</hi> intimating thereby that no War could be well begun without them, nor luckily end. Thus, in <hi>Livy,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Rhodian</hi> Ambaſſadors in their Oration made to the Senate of <hi>Rome; Certè quidem vos eſtis Romani, &amp;c. Certainly, ye are</hi> Romans <hi>indeed, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard ye place your Glory in this, that ye expect your Wars ſhould prove ſucceſsful, becauſe ye take care that they be juſt in the Cauſes of them, and that ye look to the</hi> Principia, <hi>the Beginnings of them, that they be not without cauſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, rather than to a victorious event of them.</hi> Much might be ſaid to this point out of <hi>Cicero,</hi> and others that write of theſe Laws univerſally received among Nations; but, to be ſhort, Writers on that ſubject, do generally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, that the juſt Cauſes of War are reducible to the three following Heads.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That it be undertaken for Defence. <hi>Or,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. For Recovery of what hath been taken away. <hi>Or,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. To puniſh for Injuries done.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Some one of theſe ought to be Ingredient in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of War, elſe it cannot have a juſt cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:41002:7"/>Now therefore let us examin the <hi>French</hi> War by theſe Rules. We may remember when it firſt began, the World was very much at Peace, and <hi>France</hi> ſo much beforehand in Power and Greatneſs above other Nations, that it needed not to fear any of its Neighbours, and conſequently it had no neceſſity upon it, nor occaſion for <hi>Self-defence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, the Crown of <hi>France</hi> was then ſo far from a having been robbed by any other <hi>Nation,</hi> that it had ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grandiſed its ſelf above all proportion by the ſpoils that it had made of many Nations; nor was any of the Neighbour Nations in other State and Condition in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>French</hi> Power, then as the <hi>Lark</hi> under the <hi>Hobby,</hi> not daring ſo much at to ſtir. but was glad to couch and lie cloſe under all the Oppreſſions and Rapines that had been practiſed upon them by the <hi>French.</hi> It were too tedious here to recite their Actions in their Neighbour Countries for Evidence, being notorious to the World, and to be collected anon out of our enſuing Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Moreover, the <hi>French</hi> were ſo far from having any cauſe to make War to puniſh any for Injuries done, that having been in that reſpect alſo before-hand with their Neighbours, moſt other Princes had then abundant Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and much more now to complain againſt Injuries of the higheſt nature acted upon them, and to puniſh them with ſuch Revenges as are due to the <hi>Common Enemies</hi> and Diſturbers of Mankind.</p>
               <p>And truly, we may well take it for a kind of tacite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion that they had no juſt cauſe nor occaſion for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning the preſent War, ſeeing that in a <hi>Declaration</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of a very few Lines, which the <hi>French Miniſters</hi> did put forth in the Name of their King before the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41002:7"/>
of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> there is not the leaft mention made of any cauſe, ſave that it was for their <hi>King's Glory;</hi> becauſe forſooth the <hi>Hollander</hi> had (but we were not told how) <hi>detracted from his Glory, and the Glory of his Anceſtors.</hi> Not a word of any other caufe, nor of the Glory of God, whoſe Work it is uſually to pour ſhame and contempt in the end upon all ſuch Glory.</p>
               <p>There is alſo another Point which of old hath been in Uſe, and that is a <hi>Denunciation of War</hi> before the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of it. <hi>Collegium Fecialium, a College of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds</hi> was inſtituted in old <hi>Rome,</hi> without whoſe Advice as the <hi>Roman Senate</hi> never made War; ſo having firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred it to them to conſider of the Juſtneſs of their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, if they determined the Juſtice of it, then one of the ſame Colledge was ſent to the Enemy before any act of Hoſtility on their part to denounce it. So <hi>Cicero,</hi> in his firſt Book of <hi>Oſſices, Belli quidem oequitas ſanctiſſimè Feciali Populi Romani jure proeſtripta eſt;</hi> That is to ſay, <hi>The equity of any War was moſt religiouſly determined ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of the Colledge ef Heralds:</hi> And they had certain Laws in that Colledge which were called <hi>Jura Fecialia,</hi> by which they judged of the Juſtneſs of every War before they entred upon it; and when Wars were denounced, they were called <hi>Promulgata Proelia:</hi> For Juſtice being removed, what are Wars but Grand Robberies and Murtherous Executions? Thus conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly and ſolemnly proceeded meer <hi>Heathens</hi> hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and ſhall they not then riſe up in Judgment here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after againſt ſuch <hi>French Chriſtians?</hi> for, their Miniſters not minding Right or Wrong, thought it better to begin this War by way of ſurprize upon the <hi>Dutch Republick,</hi> reckoning it a ſurer way firſt to get poſſeſſion, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to leave it to the Scrupulous Criticks of Law and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41002:8"/>
Conſcience to write and diſpute about the Juſtice of the Work: no matter whether it were righteous, as long as it was in their ſence, and by cuſtom become a Glorious Atchievement, to invade on a ſuddain and oppreſs their Neigbours, having before given the World a proof of this good quality, by ſurprizing the Dominions of <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Lorrain, Sicily,</hi> and many other Countreys.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being ſaid, and known too notorious to be denied, I ſuppoſe none can deny, That the Riſe of this War was againſt all the juſt Rules of Warlike undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And all that they, or any body elſe, can have to ſay in excuſe of them is, That they are born under a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of giving trouble to all the reſt of the World, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the preſervation of themſelves at Home; for if Wars were not found out for them abroad to entertain and exerciſe their Young Nobility at the expence of their Neighbours, <hi>France</hi> alone would be too little to ſupply them. In truth the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Nation is ſuch, that it cannot endure to live long in the idleneſs of Peace. They are of a Nature ſo hot, that there muſt be Aliment for this Fire; and if ſome were not given it from abroad, it would form to it ſelf matter at Home.</p>
               <p>To this Natural propenſion muſt be added the Cuſtom of moſt part of their Provinces, and the particular Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of Noble Families, which give ſo great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to the Elder Brothers, that they leave nothing almoſt to the Younger but their Induſtry and Sword: And whereas they rarely betake themſelves to Letters to obtain a Livelyhood, and their Quality ſuffers them not to apply themſelves to Mechanick Trades, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left to them but their legitimate Robbery of War, or common Robbery, to preſerve themſelves from want and Poverty. From hence it comes to paſs, that their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41002:8"/>
Kingdom always finds it ſelf filled with an idle and boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Youth, ready to undertake any thing, and who ſeek Employments for their Valour at whoſe coſt ſoever it be. The Liberty which they had heretofore to void this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious humour in <hi>Duelling,</hi> is at preſent taken from them by wholſom Decrees of their King; ſo that did not his Miniſters find out a Foreign vent for their Spleens, by which they might evaporate, the flame would ever be breaking forth within their own Bowels.</p>
               <p>Moreover, as the greateſt Revenues of the Crown of <hi>France</hi> riſe out of the Purſe of the People, ſo becauſe the Common Contribution cannot be exacted in times of Peace, without making a great many <hi>Male-contents;</hi> 'tis always neceſſary to feed and fume the Airy multitude with the ſmoak of ſome Conqueſts, wherein they alſo are apt to Glory, though they (Poor Creatures!) get no more by the chaining of Neighbour Nations, but to have more Fellow-Slaves, and to have their own Fetter ſet the harder on, and faſtened the firmer at their heels. To which end the Grandees are always coyning pretences of Quarrel to continue in Arms, and maintain by Forcethat Royal Authority, which hath ſo ſtrangely overflown the Limits of their Fundamental Laws. It is otherwiſe impoſſible to ſatisfie all the Princes and Great Men of the Realm, though the Princes are nothing ſo numerous now as they were in the times of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third and Fourth: ſince which they have taken it up as a principal Policy to diminiſh the Princes as faſt as they can. That is one courſe; and another is, always to hold them imploy'd in Foreign Wars; and to incite them unto Glory, that they may be conſumed e're long in ruinous Undertakings, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of their own, as well as other Nations. The Platform of which Device was firſt laid, and in part effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41002:9"/>
by <hi>Cardinal Richelieu,</hi> and in a great meaſure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleted by <hi>Mazarin,</hi> his Succeſſor in the Grand Miniſtry of State. So that you ſee how they obſerve the Rules of of Juſticewhether they deal with their own Princes and People, or with Foreigners, be it by the way of War or Peace; makiug havock of all Mankind without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe, to greaten a few of themſelves: and that their King may be ſpurr'd to drive furiouſly on, they have given his fancy a fair Proſpect of an imaginary Throne of Glory at his Jorney's end, on which they promiſe to place and elevate him above Petty Monarchs, as ſole <hi>Monarch</hi> and <hi>Emperour</hi> of the Chriſtian Univerſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECTION III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Proving, That as they have obſerved no Rule of Juſtice in making War, ſo they have had little regard to it in obſerving Peace when made.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Would not make thus bold with <hi>France,</hi> were it not that there is a neceſſity for it. It is no time now to be mealy-mouth'd (as we phraſe it) but to ſpeak out, ſeeing All that is ours is involved in the Common-fate of <hi>Europ:</hi> and our cauſe cannot but be juſt, becauſe we have had patience, and tried all manner of fair means to induce the <hi>French Miniſters</hi> to grant a Peace, and we have born their Injuries to the utmoſt; among which this hath been no ſmall one, That under pretence of allowing our <hi>King</hi> the Chriſtian office of a fair Mediatorſhip, they have at length by going at the ſame time to raviſh the reſt of <hi>Flanders,</hi> thereby ſhewn plainly to all the World, that their intent was meerly to delude and abuſe us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:41002:9"/>In handling this ſubject, it is our concern to evidence how they have violated the Law of Nations, which is common to all, and to prevent the introducing of ſuch <hi>Maxims</hi> into the World, as would deſtroy the whole Commerce of Mankind, and render Humane Societies as dangerous as the company of Lions and Tygers. We are alſo no leſs concerned, to defend the Publick Faith of Treaties againſt their <hi>Fineſſes,</hi> and ſubtle Evaſions, to preſerve the <hi>Law of Arms</hi> within the Rules and Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities which the Conſent of all Nations hath eſtabliſhed; and to remove out of the ſight of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> ſuch ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Examples, which by lamentable conſequences would expoſe the weaker to the Will and Pleaſure of the ſtronger, and would eſtabliſh <hi>Force the ſole Arbiter</hi> of all proceedings. We are to meditate ſuch Courſes and Means, as may ſtop a rapid Torrent, againſt the impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs whereof neither Peace, Marriage, Oaths, Blood, Kindred, Friendſhip, nor Condeſcenſion, can be Banks ſtrong enough to keep it within its Channel. It is to our purpoſe to defend the Common Intereſt of all States and Princes, againſt a vaſt Deſign, which hath for its Cauſe nothing but a Predominant Deſire of Conqueſts; for its End, Dominion; for its Means, Arms and Intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacies; nor for its Limits any thing but what Chance will preſcribe.</p>
               <p>In a word, it's our Buſineſs now to decide the Fortune of <hi>Europ,</hi> and to pronounce the Sentence either of its Freedom or Slavery; for betwixt theſe two, no <hi>Middle State</hi> can be attain'd, no Peace be aſſured. Other Princes muſt (as long as they can) oppoſe <hi>France</hi> to preſerve themſelves free; becauſe <hi>France</hi> will never be at reſt, till She hath hung about their Necks the <hi>Toke of Conqueſt:</hi> And if ſhe ſhould hearken in the mean time to a <hi>Pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:41002:10"/>
know that you are not to enjoy it longer than She by gaining of time to form freſh Counſels into new De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, thinks fit to make a new <hi>Rupture,</hi> and fall in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you on a ſuddain like a mighty Tempeſt. The <hi>French Faith</hi> hath of late Years been pure <hi>Punick;</hi> no ſooner given, but as ſoon broken; and She by tampering with other Princes Miniſters and Subjects, inſtructs them how to menage their Faith in point of Truth to beſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and by a Metal of her own, tries what Metal they are made of e're ſhe deals with their Maſters; and with this ſort of white Powder, which does execution with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out noiſe, ſhoots down more Caſtles, Citadels and Forts, and takes in more Towns than all the roaring of her Cannon. It hath been obſerved, That when her Ambaſſadours go abroad, they carry along with them the principal Engines, or elſe they are ſent after them. The truth of this hath been too notorious to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour at <hi>Vienna,</hi> and in <hi>Sweden, Poland, Hungary, Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, Bavaria, Munſter,</hi> and other Places of the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire;</hi> ſo that an Ambaſſadour, or an Agent, uſually goes before the Army, and a Conqueſt follows; which is a new way to Glory, unknown to <hi>Coeſar,</hi> or any of the dull <hi>Roman Conquerers.</hi> But againſt an Enemy any thing now is glorious;</p>
               <q>—<hi>An dolus, an virtus, quis in hoſte requirat?</hi>
               </q>
               <p>And if this Courſe of corrupting other Mens Faith be a Vertue, 'tis no wonder She can ſo readily, without ſtraining, quit her own, by a quick diſcharge of all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements and Obligations. Old <hi>Nicholas</hi> the <hi>Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rattles were invented to pleaſe Children, and Oaths Men:</hi> That is to ſay, to make Men meer Children.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:41002:10"/>But the beſt way to ſatisfie the World about this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, will be to give a brief Account of the Conduct and Carriage of the <hi>French Court,</hi> ſince the Miniſters which are now in Employ there appear'd upon the Stage; who are not likely to relinquiſh thoſe Methods which they were bred up in, nor to act upon any other principles than thoſe that were taught them in the School of their two <hi>Cardinal-Maſters;</hi> Of the latter of them, <hi>Mazarin,</hi> it is reported by many, that upon ſeveral occaſions he had been heard to ſay, That it was a meanneſs in a Man of State-Employment to be <hi>Eſclave de ſa Parole,</hi> A <hi>Slave to his Word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are not to ſeek for Inſtances, how he and his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples have practiſed accordingly to this very day. Let us look back as far as that grand Treaty betwixt <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> called the <hi>Pyrenean Treaty,</hi> the occaſion whereof was this,—By the Mediation of the Queen-Mother of <hi>France,</hi> a Peace was ſet on foot betwixt that Crown and <hi>Spain,</hi> with a propoſition of a Marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this King her Son, and the Lady <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain:</hi> The ends of it were alledged to be,</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>A Deſire to give eaſe and quiet to their Subjects.</l>
                  <l>To put a period to the many miſchievous Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of the War.</l>
                  <l>To forget and extinguiſh all the Cauſes and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the Wars paſt; and to eſtabliſh a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, entire, and durable Peace betwixt them and their Succeſſors.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The Treaty being begun, it was grounded upon two principal Particulars; and unleſs the <hi>French</hi> would grant thoſe, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> was reſolved not to proceed in it.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41002:11"/>
The one was, That the <hi>French ſhould forſake their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence to</hi> Portugal. The other was, That the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta</hi> ſhould, upon the Marriage, make a <hi>Renunciation</hi> (confirmed and ratified by the <hi>French</hi> King) of all her Pretences, Titles, or Claims whatſoever to the <hi>Spaniſh Monarchy,</hi> and all the Dominions thereof, or to any part of the ſame. And the Reaſon of it in the Draught of the Treaty is ſet down in theſe words; <hi>Leſt the glory of their reſpective Kingdoms ſhould happen to decay and be diminiſhed, if through the ſaid Marriage, they ſhould come to be united and conjoyned in any of their Children or Poſterity; which might occaſion to the Subjects ſuch troubles and afflictions as may eaſily be imagined.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next, as to the Excluſion and abandoning of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King obliged himſelf to it in theſe words: <hi>His ſaid Majeſty of</hi> France <hi>will intermeddle no further in the ſaid Buſineſs, and doth promiſe and oblige himſelf upon his Honour, and upon the Faith and Word of a King, both for himſelf and his Succeſſors, not to give to any Perſon or Perſons thereof, of what Dignity, Eſtate or Condition whatſoever, either at preſent, or in the future, any help or aſſiſtance, neither publick nor ſecret, directly nor indirectly, of Men, Arms, Munitions, Victualling, Veſſels, nor Money, under any pretence; nor any other thing whatſoever, by Land or by Sea, nor in any other manner: as likewiſe not to ſuffer any Levies to be made in any part of his Kingdoms and Dominions; nor to grant a paſſage to any that might come from other Countries, to the relief of the ſaid Kingdom of</hi> Portugal.</p>
               <p>Now, can any imagin more cautious and efficacious words in a Treaty, to prevent a further aſſiſtance from <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Portugal,</hi> which was the main thing that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſought for by this Marriage? Yet as ſoon as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41002:11"/>
the Treaty was penned, and before the Inſtrument was ſigned, the moſt Eminent <hi>Mazarin,</hi> ſent privately the Marquis of <hi>Chenes</hi> into <hi>Portugal,</hi> to aſſure the <hi>Portugais,</hi> That notwithſtanding he could not avoid the putting ſuch words in the Treaty, in order to the Concluſion of it, as did engage <hi>France</hi> not to aſſiſt them, howſoever they might reſt aſſured, his Maſter would never forſake them, but would continue to them an aſſiſtance as much as before.</p>
               <p>For the more full clearing of this matter, <hi>viz.</hi> That an abandoning of <hi>Portugal</hi> was one of the eſſential Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of that Peace, and that otherwiſe it could never have been treated of, nor concluded; take notice that in the <hi>60th.</hi> Article of the ſaid Treaty you may find theſe words: [<hi>Foraſmuch as we have foreſeen and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, that ſuch an Engagement might have been an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle not to be ſurmounted in the concluding of this Peace, and by conſequence would have reduced the two Kings to a neceſſity of perpetuating the War, &amp;c.</hi>]</p>
               <p>And a little after, in the ſame Article, it is further expreſſed thus, [<hi>Finally, in contemplation of the Peace, and ſeeing the abſolute neceſſity wherein his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty finds himſelf, either to perpetuate the War by a Rupture of the preſent Treaty, which he perceives to be inevitable, in caſe he ſhould have perſiſted to obtain from his Catholick Majeſty in this Affair, other conditions than thoſe which he had offered, &amp;c.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Moreover, by the ſame Article it is evident, That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>French</hi> King offered then to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> to make reſtitution of all the Places which <hi>France</hi> had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from him by Arms during the War, rather than he would have been by Treaty obliged to forbear a further aſſiſting the <hi>Portugais,</hi> the <hi>Spaniard</hi> utterly refuſed this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41002:12"/>
Offer, as is apparent by other words of the ſame Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, as they follow:</p>
               <p>[<hi>Offering, beſides the Places which are to be reſtored unto his Catholick Majeſty by the preſent Treaty, to render unto him alſo all the other Conqueſts in general which his ſaid Arms have made in this War, and intirely to reſtore the Prince of</hi> Conde; <hi>provided, and upon condition, that the Affairs of the Kingdom of</hi> Portugal <hi>ſhould remain in the State in which at preſent they are.</hi>]</p>
               <p>'Tis likewiſe out of controverſie, that this abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Portugal</hi> was covenanted and promiſed by <hi>France,</hi> ſo authentically, and in ſuch clear and ſpecial Terms, that it is not to be queſtioned, nor be made ſubject to any Interpretations contrary to the true ſence and intention of the Parties contracting; the terms whereof are theſe: [<hi>His ſaid Majeſty ſhall meddle no more with the ſaid Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, and doth promiſe and oblige himſelf upon his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and in the Faith and Word of a King, for himſelf and his Succeſſors, not to give unto the afore-mentioned Kingdom of</hi> Portugal, <hi>neither in general, nor to any Perſon or Perſons of it in particular, of what Dignity, Eſtate or Condition ſoever they may be, neither for the preſent, nor hereafter, any aid or aſſiſtance, publick or ſecret, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly, of Men, Arms, Ammunition, Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, Ships, or Moneys, under any pretext; nor of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing that is or can be, by Land or by Sea, nor in any other faſhion: As likewiſe, not to permit that any Levies ſhall be made in any of his moſt Chriſtian Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Kingdoms and Eſtates, nor grant free paſſage to thoſe which may come out of other Countries, to the help of the afore-ſaid Realm of</hi> Portugal.]</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs 'tis evident, that they immediately fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in every point and circumſtance of this Promiſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41002:12"/>
that as in the very time of the publick making of the ſaid Treaty, they were privately tampering with the <hi>Portugais,</hi> and gave them under-hand Aſſurances; ſo at the concluding of it, the Bon-fires which were every where kindled for joy of the Peace, were not quite extin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guiſh't, when an evident Breach of the Treaty was obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, in the <hi>French</hi> ſending Auxiliary Forces into <hi>Portugal</hi>-at the beginning under the Name of <hi>Mareſhal Tureine</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Troops were raiſed and convey'd into <hi>Portugal</hi> with Arms and Ammunition; as if <hi>Tureine</hi> durſt have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to do ſuch a thing, without the privity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Prime Miniſters: And when the <hi>Spaniard</hi> by his Ambaſſadour complained of this, they deluded him, by iſſuing forth publick Orders to the Governours of their Ports, that no Souldiers, or Arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould be ſuffered to imbarque for <hi>Portugal:</hi> But thoſe Governours better underſtood their private Leſſon, and ſo let them paſs by connivance. But at length they began to act openly, and notwithſtanding the Treaty they had made with <hi>Spain,</hi> they entred into an Offenſive League with <hi>Portugal</hi> againſt all its Enemies; in which the <hi>French</hi> had ſo well provided for themſelves, that by Agreement they were to have all the Sea-Towns delivered to them which ſhould be taken from the <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The truth of theſe things was not only manifeſt in Fact, but it was alſo teſtified by Letters, which the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>Spain</hi> had intercepted, that after the Peace made betwixt the two Crowns, the Court of <hi>France</hi> had fomented the War of the <hi>Portugais,</hi> hindred them from accepting thoſe advantageous Conditions which <hi>Spain</hi> had offered them; animating them by a hope of mighty Succours, not only for their defence, but alſo for carrying an Offenſive War into the very
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41002:13"/>
heart of <hi>Spain.</hi> Among theſe were many of thoſe that had been written by the <hi>French</hi> Miniſter Monſieur <hi>de Lyonne,</hi> and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Ambrun,</hi> to Monſieur <hi>de Schom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> which proved the continual correſpondence that was betwixt them for the direction of that War. And to promote it, 'tis known that in 1672. the Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> came with his whole Fleet upon the Coaſts of <hi>Portugal,</hi> where he ſpent a part of the Summer, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a paſſage of Victuals and Ammunition, whereof the <hi>Portugais</hi> were in extreme want; and this at the ſame time when they were offering <hi>Spain</hi> their Mediation to make an Accommodation with <hi>Portugal.</hi> Not to omit how one of the Prime <hi>French</hi> Miniſters, Monſieur <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> privately made ſeveral Voyages thither to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them, and contract a more ſtrict Alliance with them, and to open a way for the bringing about a League Offenſive: Which in ſome time after was concluded with the <hi>Portugais,</hi> with theſe following Conditions; [<hi>That they ſhall be the Friends of their Friends, and the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of their Enemies, excepting</hi> England. <hi>That</hi> France <hi>ſhall furniſh them with as many Men as they need, to carry on an Offenſive War in</hi> Spain <hi>both by Sea and Land; Shall advance to them by way of Loan the half of their pay, for the entertainment of Auxiliary Troops; and that they ſhall furniſh them every Year under the ſame title of Loan, with the Sum of three hundred thouſand Crowns. That all the Ports which they ſhall take in</hi> Spain, <hi>either upon the one or the other Sea, ſhall be put into the power of</hi> France. <hi>That they ſhall not treat either of Peace or Truce, without common Conſent. And that this League ſhall laſt for the ſpace of ten Years.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe particulars it is apparent, how little credit is to be given to <hi>France,</hi> in the moſt ſolemn Engagements
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41002:13"/>
that She can make to any Prince, about any Matter whatſoever. For, that a Treaty managed in order to a Marriage between Princes, (which is one of the moſt Solemn Subjects that can be handled among Men) and confirmed by Oath, with the moſt Sacred Myſteries of their Religion at the High Altar, for a Punctual ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, ſhould be thus palpably broken, is not to be parallel'd by any Inſtance or Example in all the World beſide. But 'tis not in this Buſineſs of <hi>Portugal</hi> alone that a Breach was made; that which is more conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able is, That as ſoon as the <hi>French</hi> ſaw Opportunity, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Death of the late King of <hi>Spain,</hi> they ſtarted up a Claim for their King, in the Right and Behalf of his Wife the <hi>Infanta,</hi> notwithſtanding her Solemn <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation</hi> formerly mentioned, which was entred into the Body of the Treaty, and as ſacredly ſworn to; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that a great part of the <hi>Spaniſh Low-Countreys</hi> was devolved to him in her Right, <hi>by the Municipal Laws of thoſe Countreys;</hi> whereas 'tis known, that when Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces enter into a Treaty, it is regulated and confirmed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Law of Nations</hi> common to all; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo to be underſtood, it is ridiculous among <hi>Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> to imagin that a Conſideration of <hi>Laws Municipal,</hi> or Cuſtoms, belonging to any particular Country un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Dominion of either of the Treating Princes, can intervene or be admitted afterwards to the over-throwing of the Treaty, or the depriving either of the Parties of the Benefit and Security which he hath thereby: It is a thing not to be named among States-men. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Renunciation,</hi> the Treaty had never been agreed on; and it was ſo carefully penned, as if a Grand Council of Civil Lawyers had been called to out-do all former Expreſſions uſed in ſuch Contracts, and to find out new
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41002:14"/>
binding Clauſes, to take off all poſſibility of Evaſion: And yet againſt the very Sence and End of that <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> (as all Men know) under that ſo ſlight pretence of a Claim, fell foul on a ſudden upon <hi>Flanders</hi> and other parts with their Army; which was their <hi>Firſt Invaſion</hi> upon thoſe Countries after that Treaty.</p>
               <p>But 'tis further obſervable, That this <hi>Invaſion,</hi> ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>French</hi> Engagements, and ſo deſtructive of the very Eſſence of the afore-ſaid <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty, was attended with ſome Circumſtances no leſs ſurpriſing than the Breach it ſelf. The one was that which paſſed at <hi>Paris</hi> between the Marquis <hi>de la Fuente</hi> Ambaſſadour Extraordinary of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King. And the other was what the Archbiſhop of <hi>Ambrun,</hi> Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of <hi>France</hi> in the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> declared there in his Maſter's Name.</p>
               <p>As to the firſt, <hi>Fuente</hi> having received a Call Home to <hi>Spain,</hi> and being jealous that the great Preparations then made in <hi>France</hi> were intended againſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Dominions, he thought fit to preſs the <hi>French</hi> King, to give his Miſtreſs the <hi>Queen-Regent</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> ſome new Aſſurances, that might quiet and ſettle her Mind againſt the many ſtrange Reports of his intended Preparations. Thereupon, that King did with all poſſible Aſſeveration engage <hi>His Royal Word</hi> and Faith, that he would Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly keep the Peace, and continue an entire Amity to her and the Young King her Son.</p>
               <p>As to the ſecond, note that whereas not long after, the <hi>French</hi> Army took the Field, and had poſſeſſed it ſelf of <hi>Charleroy,</hi> about four or five days before the News could arrive at <hi>Madrid:</hi> yet the ſaid Archibiſhop of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brun,</hi> being expoſtulated with about it, did <hi>in verbo Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotis,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:41002:14"/>
and upon all that is moſt ſacred among <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> proteſt and vow to the <hi>Queen-Regent,</hi> that his Maſter intended nothing leſs than what was reported of him. And that he knew he would never break with the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> nor invade any of his Dominions, as long as he was <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder Age.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>—<hi>Sic ſaevis inter ſe covenit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſis.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Oh, how well do the <hi>French Miniſters</hi> and their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours agree with one another, to effect their Maſter's Buſineſs and their own! For, it was not many days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, that News was brought to the <hi>Spaniſh Court</hi> how fairly the <hi>French</hi> had kept their word, having entred and practiſed all manner of Hoſtilities upon <hi>Flanders,</hi> firing many conſiderable Towns, and waſting the Countrey, proceeding ſo outrageouſly, and ſo far, that <hi>England</hi> and the Neighbour Princes taking the Alarm, and expoſtulating the matter with <hi>France,</hi> it brought on another Treaty, which was held at <hi>Aken,</hi> i. e. <hi>Aix la Chapelle,</hi> to make a New Agreement betwixt <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> about the Obſervation whereof we have afforded us another In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the <hi>French</hi> Fidelity.</p>
               <p>Unto this <hi>Treaty</hi> all the Princes of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> were invited, to take care of the common Security; and his Majeſty of <hi>England</hi> among the reſt, who ſent alſo a Miniſter to the Proteſtant Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> to invite them into the Guaranty of the ſaid Treaty of <hi>Aix.</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals alſo were made to the Duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Princes, to come into the League then to be made, to which the <hi>Lorainer</hi> immediately accorded, hoping that by this <hi>Treaty</hi> he might have better luck with the <hi>French,</hi> than he formerly had with them by the <hi>Pyrenean Treaty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41002:15"/>But before we proceed, it will not be amiſs to remember you, How the <hi>French</hi> kept Faith with this poor Prince, whoſe Intereſts had been provided for by the ſaid Treaty, as well as thoſe of <hi>Spain,</hi> and his Dutchy to be reſtored to him, with all the Places and Towns which he had been poſſeſſed of within the Biſhopricks of <hi>Metz, Toul,</hi> and <hi>Verdun.</hi> But ſee how <hi>France</hi> dealt with him: They deferr'd as long as they could the performance of that part which related to the ſaid <hi>Duke,</hi> and refuſed ſtill to return him his Country, till they had brought him to make another Treaty with them in prejudice of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; whereby he was forced to part with ſeveral conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Places, over and above what had been granted to them by the <hi>General Peace.</hi> And yet this would not ſerve their turn: For, after the oppreſſed <hi>Duke</hi> had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd a Year and a half but a very unſettled poſſeſſion, during which, under ſeveral artificial unjuſt pretences, new Quarrels were pick't every day, they with a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Army conſtrained him to give them his Town of <hi>Marſal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, it was but a little time after this, that they fell to teazing him again, compelling him to ſign a New Treaty more diſadvantageous to him than the two former, and yet (ſo inſatiable is their Appetite after <hi>Dominion</hi>) the unhappy <hi>Duke</hi> could, as little as before, obtain a quiet enjoyment of that little they had left him. They every day encroached upon his Juriſdiction, the limits of his Territories, and his Soveraignty it ſelf. They impoſed grievous Taxes upon his Subjects. They cauſed him to disband his Forces, and to raiſe new Men again, as they thought fit. They kept him from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging his own Quarrels, to take part in others. They let looſe all his Enemies againſt him, and ſtopped the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41002:15"/>
progreſs of his Armies, as ſoon as he had got the leaſt Advantage: And in few words, he was at that time more a Vaſſal to <hi>France</hi> than a Soveraign in his own Country. But yet all this would not ſatisfie the <hi>French Court;</hi> they muſt have all again: wherefore the <hi>Duke</hi> by many Circumſtances ſhewing how ill he brook't this kind of unreaſonable uſage, They ordered one of their Generals to ſurpriſe and ſeize his Perſon, and to bring him either dead or alive: Of which intended violence having had timely notice, he eſcaped when it was very near being effected. <hi>Which</hi> (as one very well obſerved) <hi>is a new way of dealing with a Soveraign Prince, not known before in theſe parts of the World; and it may teach all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes what to truſt to in treating, and what to expect from ſuch monſtrous Neighbours: And it gives us ſome hope, that we may e're long live to ſee the Weſt govern'd by</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaws <hi>as well as the Eaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No other thing could give us a better In-ſight into the Ambition and Pride, nor more fully diſcover the Intent and Deſign of <hi>France.</hi> None but an <hi>Univerſal Monarch</hi> can pretend to an Arbitrary diſplacing of Princes, and a diſpoſing of their Liberty, Lives, and Territories........... Thus you ſee how perſidiouſly they dealt with the Duke of <hi>Lorain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to return to the Treaty of <hi>Aix.</hi> It proved to be of little avail to that Duke. For, they have ſince ſeiz'd his Country again, and driven him out to ſeek his Fortune; and this (as Men ſay) for no other Reaſon, but becauſe he hoped by this Treaty to have confirmed himſelf among his Allies in a better State of Security than he had hitherto been. And as for the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> alſo reſolved to defeat their Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of benefit by this <hi>Treaty:</hi> for contrary to it, they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41002:16"/>
preſently fell to work; Firſt they diſmantled all the ſtrong Places and Holds of the Country of <hi>Burgundie,</hi> carried away all the Munitions out of it, and would have ſpoiled the rich Salt-pits of that Province, Had not the Powerful interpoſition both of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</p>
               <p>In deſpite alſo of that <hi>Treaty,</hi> they exacted great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions from the Dutchies of <hi>Limbourg</hi> and <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg.</hi> They laid a new Claim to ſome Towns, as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant as any of thoſe that were granted to them by the Peace. They confiſcated the Eſtates of the Subjects of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> that would not forſwear their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and ſpared not the very Royal Houſe of <hi>Mary Mont.</hi> Nay, as if theſe Infractions were not enough, and ſtill to encroach as far as they were able, they forced their way with great quantities of Merchandiſe through the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Territories, without paying the Cuſtoms, and not long after endeavoured to ſurpriſe the Town of <hi>Hainault.</hi> In a word, They did whatever they pleas'd, plunder'd even the moſt Sacred Places, and acted whatever can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined to be done, without remorſe, by inſolent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable men.</p>
               <p>But to proceed; it muſt not be forgotten, How under a pretence of advancing the Affairs of <hi>Poland,</hi> and ſetling an Amity there, they contrived a Marriage for that King with a Lady of <hi>France;</hi> by which means they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to ſend thither along with her in her Train, ſo many expert Inſtruments of miſchief, that immediately they ſettled a <hi>Cabal</hi> with ſuch Intrigues, as in a ſhort time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed the Nobility of that Kingdom into heats and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions againſt one another, which are never likely to be extinguiſh't; and at that time they operated ſo far, that that King ſoon became willing to quit the Kingdom; and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41002:16"/>
thereupon the <hi>Turk</hi> ſeeing the great Diviſions that were wrought among them, was eaſily invited in by the <hi>French Cabal,</hi> meerly becauſe they could not bring in a King that was of <hi>French Blood,</hi> or of <hi>French Intereſt,</hi> at the following Election. And alſo to this, That one of the greateſt Motives of their fetching in the <hi>Turk,</hi> was, that their New King contracted Marriage with the <hi>Emperour's</hi> Siſter; which Princeſs being now a Widdow, is ſhortly to be married to the Duke of <hi>Lorain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is worth the while alſo to remember how finely they uſed the Duke of <hi>Newbourg</hi> while they trained him on to engage the greateſt part of his Eſtate, almoſt beyond redemption, in hopes of getting the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Crown, which they had promiſed to procure for him by the help of a ſtrong Party which they had made in that Kingdom. Yet under-hand, and contrary to their Treaties, as well with the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> as with himſelf, and to their iterated Promiſes and Vows, both by word of Mouth, and in Writing, they did by their Creatures and Agents oppoſe the ſaid Duke's pretenſions, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured with all Induſtry to have gotten the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> preferred before all his Competitors: a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Account whereof would, if publiſhed, without any other Inſtance, be a ſufficient warning to all other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and afford them a perfect Character of the <hi>French</hi> Court.</p>
               <p>But 'tis remarkable, That it is not with Princes alone that they thus finely deal; but they obſerve alſo juſt the ſame meaſure of Faith toward ſuch Rebels and Traytors of their making, as they have gained for Money, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the Concerns of their own Country, by ſerving the Intrigues and Intereſts of <hi>France.</hi> For, when after the beginning of this War, they ſaw the <hi>Emperour</hi> ſetting
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41002:17"/>
himſelf in good earneſt to aſſiſt the <hi>Dutch,</hi> then to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade and divert him from his purpoſe, and to engage him (if it had been poſſible) not to concern himſelf or take part in the Quarrel, they very fairly offer'd him to deliver into his hands all the Original Letters and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers they had received from time to time from their bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Friends and Creatures in <hi>Poland,</hi> to the end that both his <hi>Imperial Majeſty,</hi> and his Brother-in-Law the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> might take what courſe they thought ſit with thoſe Traitors. Which handſom Story may ſerve as a fair Warning and Fright to all thoſe that prefer <hi>French</hi> Money before their Loyalty, and the true Intereſts of their Country. And truly, this piece of Inſidelity in the <hi>French</hi> is the only Piece of Juſtice that I find them guilty of, in the management of Affairs with their Friends and Correſpondents.</p>
               <p>But withal I find, that this piece of their kindneſs to his <hi>Imperial Majeſty,</hi> was to make him amends for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prank of Treachery that had been plaid him a while before. For the <hi>moſt Chriſtian Miniſters</hi> pretending a courteſie to aſſiſt him againſt the <hi>Turk,</hi> and accordingly having ſent Forces to joyn with the <hi>Imperial</hi> Army, they at the very ſame time began to ſettle a Correſpondence with Count <hi>Serini, Frachipani, Nadaſti,</hi> and <hi>Tottenbach;</hi> as did afterwards appear upon the breaking out of the Conſpiracy, when the Depoſitions and Confeſſions of ſome of the Accomplices were produced, who had been inſtrumental in carrying both Monies and Letters from the <hi>French Miniſter</hi> reſident at <hi>Vienna,</hi> to the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators.</p>
               <p>Next, let us have recourſe to the <hi>Swedes,</hi> and examin whether they, having been many years their very good Friends and humble Servants, have had better luck in treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41002:17"/>
with them than others, in point of dealing. But ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Siveden</hi> cannot forget, that almoſt twenty Years ago they had occaſion to make a Treaty with them whereby they were to receive by way of Gratuity or Penſion Sixteen Hundred Thouſand Crowns. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, upon ſecond thoughts, the <hi>French</hi> finding their Treaty with <hi>Sweden</hi> to be but of little uſe to them at that time, refuſed to ratifie it, and ſent Monſieur <hi>de Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> his Ambaſſadour to them, to tell them in ſhort, That the King his Maſter declared it to be void. Which is a fine Court-ſtile for one Prince to uſe to another in Treating; and a tart, ſhort, Majeſtick way of reſcinding Treaties.</p>
               <p>It were both needleſs and tedious to tell, how well they have obſerved their Treaties with <hi>Holland,</hi> ſeeing they cannot ſo much as aſſign the leaſt Cauſe of the War they now make againſt them, foraſmuch as in their Declaration they told us only of a <hi>Mauvaiſe ſatisfaction,</hi> and that they were ill pleaſed; and that it would tend to a diminution of the Glory of the <hi>moſt Chriſtian King,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to pleaſe himſelf he put all <hi>Europ</hi> in a Flame, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to bring all under his ſubjection.</p>
               <p>It is pleaſant likewiſe to obſerve, how they practiſed their Art alſo upon that notable Fox the Biſhop of <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> how they not only lurch't him during his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt with the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> but their <hi>French</hi> Troops fell alſo upon him, and indangered the loſs of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. How they another time brought him about to lurch us in <hi>England,</hi> by reducing him to a neceſſity of ſeparating from our Intereſt, after he had received aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from us in a good Sum of Money. How they hindred the <hi>Swedes</hi> from arming in our favour, and ſway'd <hi>Denmark</hi> from our Party during our War with the <hi>Dutch</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:41002:18"/>
even at the ſame time when <hi>France</hi> ſeem'd to forward and favour us againſt <hi>Holland;</hi> and it hath been often publiſhed, that they then ſpurr'd on the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and were in with them in the contrivance of that Affront which they did us in the River of <hi>Thames;</hi> thereby reckoning, that ſo ſevere an exaſperation would neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follow in our Minds againſt <hi>Holland,</hi> as might ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us irreconcileable to them, and engage us in War ſo long, till we ſhould waſte and wear out one another's Men and Shipping, that we might at laſt be the leſs able to oppoſe <hi>France,</hi> who was at that time meditating and forming ſuch a mighty Advance of her own Naval Power, as might inable her to contend againſt us both, when We ſhould ſee it our Intereſt to unite againſt her hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And the truth is, the <hi>French Miniſters</hi> did herein act according to a right underſtanding of their own Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs: For, they did and do very well know, that in order to the main End of graſping All, they ought to dread no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than a durable and firm Friendſhip between us and the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> as that alone that can ſet bounds to their Ambition, and redeem <hi>Europ</hi> from that <hi>Toke</hi> which they are framing, and deviſing how to put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout our Necks. Therefore it was dextrouſly done of them to find out a fine Artifice of Treachery to delude us both, and to ſpin out that War: For, in the very heat of the War, they kept Negotiations ſtill on foot, both in <hi>England</hi> and at the <hi>Hague;</hi> put on a diſguiſe of <hi>Mediation,</hi> pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make us Friends; and to that purpoſe made Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Propoſals of Peace. It might be told who were ſaid to be the Inſtruments on both ſides, to puſh on this project of deluſion upon us ſo far, that we in <hi>England</hi> were aſſured by the <hi>French,</hi> that the <hi>Dutch</hi> were ſo well inclin'd to Peace, that for that time they meant to lay up their Men
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41002:18"/>
of War; but then afterwards the <hi>French</hi> under hand preſſed the ſaid <hi>Dutch</hi> with all vigour and earneſtneſs imaginable againſt us, and to fit out their Men of War again, promiſing that rather than fail they would joyn theirs to them againſt us. It was upon a ſuppoſal the <hi>French</hi> were true to us at that time in carrying on their pretended Propoſals of Peace, that we were made ſecure, ſlackned our Preparations that Year; and ſo a ſurpriſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed upon it; for, the <hi>Dutch</hi> having been <hi>Tarantulated</hi> with a <hi>French Brieze</hi> in their Tails, danced after the Leſſon they had ſet them, and ſo entred our River as high as <hi>Chatham:</hi> thus it was brought about, as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port went in thoſe days. However, admit it ſhould not be true that the <hi>French</hi> were the Authors of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, yet 'tis unqueſtionable they knew of the Deſign e're the Attempt was made; it was their pretence of bringing about a Peace that rendred us ſecure, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we had no Security but in War, or in a Peace of our own making. Which may ſufficiently inſtruct us at our own coſt, what Security is to be expected from <hi>French Amity</hi> and <hi>Treaty.</hi> It was not long after, that we began to ſee a Convenience of Peace; inſomuch that a <hi>Treaty</hi> was concluded at <hi>Breda:</hi> and where as one Article was, That the <hi>French</hi> ſhould reſtore unto us <hi>St. Chriſtophers,</hi> in the manner and form therein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, nevertheleſs they began again to abuſe us, and inſtead of performing it according to the very letter and true meaning of the Article, they ſtill from time to time upon ſeveral unjuſt and frivolous Pretences, put off his Majeſties Commiſſioners that went to receive it, till ſeeing a neceſſity to comply with us in ſo ſmall a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they after four years baffling, were pleas'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver it. But 'tis to be noted, That before the delivery
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41002:19"/>
of it they deſtroy'd all the plantations, plunder'd and carried away all that was portable, laid the whole Country waſte, and left it in a worſe condition than if it had been never planted. And as if the detaining of his Majeſties Territories had not been ſufficient, they interrupted the Trade of his Majeſties Subjects in thoſe parts: and aſſuming to themſelves a Sovereignty in thoſe Seas, they would not ſuffer any Ships but of their own Nation, to ſail by, or about their Iſlands: and upon no other Ground proceeded ſo far, as to bring in many Veſſels as Prizes, and confiſcate them.</p>
               <p>But 'tis not in the <hi>Weſt-India</hi> Trade only that we have been thus uſed: but they have been many years, and ſtill are, diminiſhing our Trade here at home. They deſign upon our Cloth-Trade, and many of our uſefull Manufactures, by Money tempting away the Makers of them to go and ſettle in <hi>France,</hi> and by them get their own People to be inſtructed in the making of them. And in the mean while, to advance and encourage their own Manufacture; and cauſe ours to lie upon our own hands when made, they lay heavy Impoſitions upon all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cloth, Stuffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that are or ſhall be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported into <hi>France;</hi> which is the ready way to blow up many of our Merchants, and moſt of our Manufactures, and undoe Thouſands of poor People who depend upon them for a Subſiſtance by Work. No wonder then it hath been obſerved, That we do not of late ſend into <hi>France</hi> the Fourth or Fifth part of what Goods and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities we formerly ſent over. Nay, I hear, That Monſieur <hi>Colbert,</hi> one of their principal Miniſters, is at this very time conſulting and adviſing with Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and others, to give our Trade a further diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; while we (ſuch is the fondneſs of our Nation!) are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41002:19"/>
bewitched with an affectation of <hi>French</hi> Commodities, though but meer <hi>Baubles</hi> and <hi>Gugaws,</hi> and though our own Workmen afterwards work better, and out-do them in the making of their own Inventions, yet (ſuch is our baſe folly!) unleſs the Retailers of them do ſwear, and lie too, that they are <hi>French</hi>-made, there's no putting them off to advantage at a quick rate. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, we muſt have all <hi>French</hi> about us; their Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, their Faſhions, their Garb in wearing them, their mean way of Houſe-keeping (to the utter extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Noble way of Old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hoſpitality) their needy men for Servants, their meer Dietary Leeches or Scholaſtick Methodiſts (no better than moſt of our own) for Phyſicians; their caſt Tooth-drawers and Barbers that had not worth enough to earn Bread at home, to become our admired Chirurgions; <hi>French</hi> Muſick, <hi>French</hi> Dancing - Maſters, <hi>French</hi> Air in our very Countenances, <hi>French</hi> Legs, <hi>French</hi> Hats, <hi>French</hi> Compliments, <hi>French</hi> Grimaces; only we have not ſo frequent the <hi>French</hi> ſhrug of the ſhoulder, becauſe we are not generally ſo low—and itchy. Pardon me, if thus far, in zeal to mine own Nation, and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I a little digreſs. Any thing that ſpeaks <hi>French</hi> is our delight; and ſuch is the Witchcraft alſo upon the other Nations of <hi>Europ,</hi> that having made the <hi>French</hi> Language and Humors Univerſal, I cannot but look on it as a ſad <hi>Omen</hi> of Univerſal Slavery; for as much as both Divines and Politicians have, by the courſe of God's Providence, and Revolutions paſt in the World, obſerved, that a Nations taking of Language from another Nation, and preferring it before their own, hath uſually bin a fore-runner of, and prepared the way for its Conqueſt. No marvel then that <hi>France</hi> is carried on
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41002:20"/>
and elevated with the Ambition and belief of Conquering All, when they ſee all ſo fancifully dote upon their more effeminate Language, Faſhions, and People. Therefore 'tis high time that we return to our <hi>Old Engliſh Spirit</hi> and Humor, which naturally is more grave, manly, and Martial, and by its native couragious Temper ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently enabled (as of old) to cure their hot fits, and cudgel them out of their diſciplinary, artificial Conduct, and evaporating Valour.</p>
               <p>But to return where I left, let me ſay, there's much more fear of their pretended Friendſhip, and certain Falſhood, than of any thing elſe they can do, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their Numbers; as may be collected out of the memorable Stories of <hi>Creſſy</hi> and <hi>Agincourt;</hi> of which laſt they have in their Chronicle left this diſmal Note, <hi>LaMau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaiſe Journée d'Agincourt.</hi> Let us then in the mean time have an eye to their Treachery, Treaties, Peace more dangerous than War, and their abuſive Dealings.</p>
               <p>And if thoſe Particulars which we have hitherto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, be not enough to paint them out in their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, let us next call to mind how falſly they dealt with us in the laſt <hi>Dutch War,</hi> under pretence and appearance of a hearty Conjunction with us. As to the undertaking it ſelf, they made us to believe they would be Principal in the War, and that they would be content that our Forces ſhould ſecond them but as <hi>Auxiliaries:</hi> but as ſoon as they thought they had engag'd us ſo far in the buſineſs, that we could not well go back, nor take new Counſels, they in all Princes Courts declared it was not their Quarrel, and that they were engaged in it only to aſſiſt us. Which was a friendly courſe to render us as liable as they could to the Diſpleaſure of other Princes that liked not the War; and to excuſe themſelves,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41002:20"/>
though they had bin the chief Cauſers and Contrivers of it.</p>
               <p>We cannot omit to remind you next, how ſtrangely they behaved themſelves towards us by Sea; When they ſhould have aſſiſted us in the Battle that was fought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Conduct of the moſt Illuſtrious his Highneſs Prince <hi>Rupert;</hi> when by reaſon of their ſtanding at a diſtance in the very heat and ſtreſs of the Fight, and never coming in to aſſiſt him, they did ſufficiently ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that their Squadron of Ships was ſent only to be Spectators, and to learn to Fight, and for other ends, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to act in it: and truly his Highneſs that day gave them an Heroick Example of Skill and Courage, when he was ſet upon by two of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Squadrons toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, one of which the <hi>Admiral</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron ought to have engag'd, according to the Orders that his Highneſs had ſent to him the day before: but he not coming in, though the wind all the day ſtood fair for him, his Highneſs was left alone to bear the brunt of the Engagement with two of the Enemies Squadrons at once: and though his own Ship was ſurrounded on all ſides, yet he ſo nobly acquitted himſelf that day, that he not only made his own way out of that great diſtreſs, but giving a Couragious Example to the reſt of his Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, went with them, and aſſiſted that other Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of ours which had been engaged againſt Vice-Admiral <hi>Tromp</hi> at a great diſtance in a ſeparate Fight, contrary to his <hi>Highneſſes</hi> Orders. Moreover, it is to be remembred, that as he made way to their Aſſiſtance, his Squadron by the way ſtill fought the <hi>Dutch</hi> Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons, who made way alſo ſide by ſide with ours at ſome diſtance, both ſides ſhooting at each other; the <hi>Dutch,</hi> in hope to have hindred the <hi>Prince</hi> from giving the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41002:21"/>
aſſiſtance intended; which being nevertheleſs effected by his Highneſs, and the <hi>Hollanders Admirals</hi> finding they could not prevent it, and that they had enough of it, made ſail away for their own Coaſts. But had the <hi>French Squadron</hi> under the Command of the Count <hi>D'Eſtrees,</hi> done his Duty, and come in to ſecond the <hi>Prince</hi> any hour of the day, as he eaſily might have done (the wind ſtanding fair) it was evident that day, we might then have had one of the moſt glorious Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories that ever was obtain'd by Sea, and but few of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships could have eſcaped home. This was afterwards acknowledged and atteſted by Monſieur <hi>Martel,</hi> the Count <hi>D'Eſtrees</hi> own Vice-Admiral, who, like an honeſt man, attempted to have come in with a few of his Ships, but could not; and afterwards for his forwardneſs to have fought, and becauſe he blamed his Admiral, when he returned to <hi>Paris,</hi> he was call'd to an Account, and Committed to Priſon; whereas the <hi>Count</hi> having followed the <hi>private Inſtructions</hi> of the <hi>French Miniſters,</hi> was ſtill continued in Honour and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. And therefore it muſt needs be an undeniable Evidence, that he had <hi>privy Orders</hi> and Inſtructions only to ſtand ſtill and look on, while we and the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſhould be tearing and deſtroying one another; becauſe otherwiſe, in order to a vindication of the Honour of <hi>France</hi> and its <hi>Miniſters,</hi> They would doubtleſs have made him anſwer that egregious Piece of Treachery with the price of his Head.</p>
               <p>I intend as much brevity as may be, therefore have forborn to touch upon all the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair: but thus much is abſolutely neceſſary, to give you proof of the <hi>French</hi> good will and faithfulneſs to <hi>England,</hi> as well as to all other Nations that have
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41002:21"/>
had, or ſhall have any Dealings with them. Now let us next ſee how they dealt with us, in order to the putting an end to this; which having been by us entred into joyntly with the <hi>French,</hi> doubtleſs nothing ought to have been attempted by any one in order to the ending of it, but what ſhould carry a fair Reſpect to the Intereſt of both Parties in conjunction: But ſee how they play'd their parts with us in this alſo!—The <hi>StatesGeneral</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> having nominated ſeveral Deputies to be ſent, ſome to his Majeſty of <hi>England,</hi> and ſome to the <hi>French King,</hi> to know of them both upon what Terms they would be willing to agree, and come to a Peace: His Majeſty (as it is a Vertue innate in his own Royal Temper) intended to deal moſt juſtly with the <hi>French King</hi> upon this occaſion; and therefore ſo carried the matter, to avoid giving him any offence or jealouſie; and being loth to do any thing in the Affair without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of Counſels, immediately ſent him word, ſuch <hi>Deputies</hi> were arrived at <hi>London,</hi> and would not ſo much as hear what their Errand was without the privity of <hi>France,</hi> ſuppoſing that he ſhould have a ſuitable Return from thence.</p>
               <p>But what happened in the mean time? Even a quite contrary behaviour of the <hi>French:</hi> For, no ſooner were the other Deputies arrived at the <hi>French Court,</hi> but they were preſently viſited and careſſed by two Secretaries of State, and without further delay it was demanded of them, firſt if they had full power from their Maſters to treat; and next, what Propoſals they would make in order to a ſpeedy Peace. The <hi>Deputies</hi> deſired rather to know firſt what Propoſals the <hi>French Miniſters</hi> would make. Whereupon, to haſten them to a Concluſion of the Work, the <hi>French</hi> ſhortly told them, they were to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41002:22"/>
underſtand, That what their Maſter the King had Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by his Arms in <hi>Holland</hi> he would not part with, unleſs they gave him an Equivalent, as well for thoſe Places, as for the reſt that he ſhould conquer before the Treaty be concluded.</p>
               <p>This Anſwer made, the Deputies forthwith ſend back one of their number to the <hi>Hague,</hi> by name Mr. <hi>De Groot,</hi> who was ſpeeded back again with Inſtructions to <hi>Amerongen,</hi> authorizing him and his Fellow-Deputies to conclude a Peace with the <hi>French.</hi> He was no ſooner arrived, but Monſieur <hi>de Louvoy</hi> one of the Prime Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of State made ſhort Work, delivered the <hi>Dutch</hi> Deputies a <hi>Project of Treaty,</hi> or rather the Pretenſions of the King his Maſter; upon grant whereof (as he ſaid) he would be both willing and ready to return to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Amity with the <hi>States General,</hi> and conclude a firm Peace with them.</p>
               <p>Was not this a ſweet Return of dealing towards his Majeſty of <hi>England?</hi> For, you to are note, That though the War was made joyntly, and ſo no doubt it was not to be ended without reſpects to be had to the Intereſts of each Party concerned therein, which you have ſeen was fairly meant and obſerved by his Majeſty on our part to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>French;</hi> yet they had ſo little regard of us, that they not only put on and entred upon a Treaty without our Privity or Conſent, but would have concluded it upon that ſeparate Treaty without us, only to their own Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, whereby their Maſter might as perfectly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſole Maſter of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> as if he he had conquered all by the <hi>Sword.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You are to note alſo, for a clearer underſtanding of their Intents, That when the Heer <hi>De Groot</hi> being to go the ſecond time from <hi>Amerongen</hi> to the <hi>Hague</hi> with the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41002:22"/>
Articles of this <hi>Separate Treaty;</hi> when he arrived there, the <hi>States</hi> finding that there was nothing in them which concerned <hi>England,</hi> he told them the <hi>French Miniſters</hi> had told him, The <hi>Sates</hi> his Maſters might deal as they pleaſed with <hi>England,</hi> and make an end as cheap as they would; becauſe (as they pretended) they were not bound by Treaty to procure the <hi>Engliſh</hi> any Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And thus no more Notice was taken of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, nor greater care of his Intereſts, than if he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been concerned in the War, or in no <hi>League</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> at all: So that if by wonderful Providence this <hi>Separate Treaty</hi> had not been broken off, <hi>Europ</hi> might have been in greater hazard of its Liberty, and we of our Safety, by a ſettled Domination of the <hi>French</hi> in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Much more might be added, to ſhew the foul play of the <hi>French</hi> with us at that time, and afterwards alſo when the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> and My Lord <hi>Arlington</hi> were ſent hence into <hi>Holland:</hi> but I muſt be brief, this being enough to diſcover their friendly behaviour during the Joynt-War <hi>An.</hi> 1673.</p>
               <p>In the next place, let us ſee how they have carried themſelves ſince the Year 73. For, we have an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that notwithſtanding the Amity betwixt us hath been continued to this Day, yet that Nation hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ceaſed to do us one Injury or other, and no ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Redreſs at all hath been obtained, though Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints have been made, and Reparation earneſtly ſought for. Witneſs eſpecially the many Affronts and Violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces done to us upon our Merchants Ships at Sea by the <hi>French Privateers:</hi> For, but very few of them have been reſtored; and thoſe that have been, have found the Remedy worſe than the Diſeaſe, becauſe the tedious delay
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41002:23"/>
of it brought ſuch charge to the Merchants, that the benefit coming by the Reſtitution would not counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail their Expences in attendance at the Court of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the Clearing whereof, it cannot be amiſs to give here at large an Account touching the Event of ſuch Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications as have been made to his Majeſty for Redreſs at the Council-board, and with the Commitee of Trade be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to his moſt Honourable <hi>Privy-Council,</hi> excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly penned, and now come to my Hand newly print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſperſed; therefore I reprint it. And it here followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="petition">
                           <div type="part">
                              <opener>
                                 <dateline>
                                    <date>At the Court at <hi>White-Hall</hi> the 4. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1676. Preſent The King's moſt excellent Majeſty in Council.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                              </opener>
                              <argument>
                                 <p>The Right Honourable the Lords of the Committee of Trade did this Day preſent unto his Majeſty in Council, a Report touching the Injuries which his Subjects did ſuſtain by <hi>French</hi> Capers, in the Words following:</p>
                              </argument>
                              <opener>
                                 <salute>May it pleaſe your Majeſty,</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>There was preſented unto your Majeſty in Council on the 31. of <hi>May</hi> laſt, a Petition in the Name of all the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of <hi>London,</hi> and other places, concerned in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ships taken by the <hi>French Privateers,</hi> and carried into ſeveral Ports of that Kingdom; and their Complaints conſiſted of the Points following:</p>
                              <p>1. That the Ships and Goods of your Majeſty's Subjects, though manned according to the Act of Navigation, and furniſhed with all neceſſary Paſſes, were daily ſeized, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into <hi>Dunkirk, Calais, Sherbrook,</hi> and other Ports,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41002:23"/>
the Maſters and Mariners kept cloſe Priſoners, to force them by hardſhip to abuſe the Owners, or elſe for Relief of their own neceſſities (being commonly ſtripped and plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) to enter into the <hi>Privateer</hi>'s Service, which great numbers have done with very pernicious effects.</p>
                              <p>2. That the delay and charge of proſecuting the Law in <hi>France,</hi> does commonly make the Owners to become loſers of half the value, when ever they are ſucceſsful.</p>
                              <p>3. That there is no Reparation ever gotten from <hi>Priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers,</hi> for what they plunder and imbezle, which makes them freely ſeize upon all they meet, and perpetually moleſt the Navigation of your Subjects.</p>
                              <p>Wherefore your Petitioners humbly imploring your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie's Protection and Relief, your Majeſty was hereupon graciouſly pleaſed, out of a ſence of your Subjects ſufferings, to command that ſome Frigats ſhould ſail forth to clear the Coaſt of thoſe <hi>Privateers,</hi> to ſeize them, and bring ſuch as had offended to make Reſtitution. And your Majeſty did fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther order, that the Committee of Trade ſhould well take notice of the particular Caſes and Complaints depending, that ſuch of them as were of weight and merit might be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to receive your moſt gracious Recommendation, for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, as to ſurvey the whole number of Seizures which have been made on your Subjects, in order to lay before your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty what hardſhips have been ſuſtained at Sea, and what ſort of Juſtice hath been adminiſtred in <hi>France,</hi> with their Opinion of what is ſit to adviſe your Majeſty therein.</p>
                              <p>In obedience to which Command we have hereunto annexed a liſt of ſuch ſhips as have bin ſeized, to the number of 53. and the Caſes wherein the Owners have repaired unto your Majeſty either in your Council, or by your Secretary of State, for Relief; which as in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral it ſuppoſes a Juſtice in ſuch Complaints, ſo it leaves
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41002:24"/>
a ſuſpicion of great hardſhip in the Methods of Redreſs, and the number of Captures is no ſmall proof of the facility of Condemnation.</p>
                              <p>How many other helpleſs Men there have been (beſides the ſaid Caſes) who have not had ability to proſecute, or how many of theſe Caſes have been favoured with Redreſs, we cannot certainly underſtand, till the Information we have ſought for, comes from <hi>Paris,</hi> which may alſo enable us to compleat their Circumſtances of every Caſe.</p>
                              <p>But in the mean time, ſuch of all the Inſtances of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, as are come to our knowledg, we have not failed in the Margin, to make mention of them, being in number ſeven.</p>
                              <p>While we were in the midſt of this Proſecution, Mr. Secretary <hi>Coventry</hi> does on the <hi>6th.</hi> inſtant preſent unto the Committee a Paper, which he received from the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour, Monſieur <hi>Courtin,</hi> relating to theſe matters, and the Contents thereof were as follow.</p>
                              <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                                 <body>
                                    <head>An Extract of a Letter from Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi> to Monſieur <hi>de Pompone,</hi> one of the <hi>French</hi> King's Secretaries, written the <hi>28th.</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 1676.</head>
                                    <p>For what concerns the Prizes, it would be a difficult matter to anſwer to all the Caſes contained in Monſieur <hi>Courtin</hi>'s Letter; What I can ſay is,</p>
                                    <p>That the Council for Marine Affairs, ſits every Friday at <hi>Saint Germans.</hi>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>That all Privateers and Reclaimers know it.</p>
                                    <p>That Sir <hi>Ellis Leighton,</hi> nominated by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, hath always notice of it, and is always pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at it.</p>
                                    <p>That not a Week paſſes, but I give him two or three
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41002:24"/>
Audiences, and often-times I ſend for him on purpoſe.</p>
                                    <p>His reaſons are all reported, read, and examined.</p>
                                    <p>As likewiſe are all Petitions of Reclaimers, and I ſhall tell you more, I acquaint him wiih the Reaſons upon which Judgment is given.</p>
                                    <p>In giving Judgment, all Veſſels which have any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of being <hi>Engliſh,</hi> are realeas'd, and very often, and almoſt always, although we are ſatisfied that the Ships are <hi>Dutch,</hi> yet they are releaſed becauſe there is ſome appearance of their being <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and every thing is judged favourable for that Nation; and it is true that all Ships that are taken are of <hi>Dutch</hi>-built, that they never were in <hi>England,</hi> that the Maſters and all the Equipage are <hi>Dutch.</hi> that the Documents are for Perſons unknown, and which are not often-times ſo much as named, that they carry with them only ſome Sea-Briefs from <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> or ſome other Town of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or <hi>Scotland:</hi> That the whole Ships Company depoſes, they were ſent to <hi>Holland,</hi> that we have found on Board, three or four Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, Bills of Accounts, by which it is ſeen the <hi>Engliſh</hi> took two, three, and four <hi>per Cent:</hi> for owning of Ships: and although it is impoſſible to avoid confiſcating them, yet theſe are the Ships which make ſuch a noiſe in <hi>England.</hi>
                                    </p>
                                 </body>
                              </floatingText>
                              <p>In anſwer to which remarks, though it be true that all reſpect imaginable ought to be given to what Miniſters of that conſideration do pronounce, yet there being ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereuae between them who feel the ſmart, and thoſe who feel it not, we ſhall inſiſt on ſome particulars, that your Majeſty may diſcern whether your Subjects are fortunate in their Freedom of Trade at Sea, or in the helps of Juſtice when they are ſeiz'd, as the Report and Information of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will ſeem to make out; for as it magnifies the favour
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41002:25"/>
which is exerciſed in <hi>France,</hi> the facility in all Addreſſes, and the tenderneſs to relieve <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men in all Complaints, ſo we cannot on this ſubject but own to your Majeſty the very different reſentments we have thereof: for we underſtand that when <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships are brought into the Ports of <hi>France,</hi> many of the Mariners complaining of ill treatment, and ſome of torment, their Papers being ſeized, and their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in reſtraint, till all examinations are prepared, then are all their Writings ſent up to the Privy-Counſel at <hi>Saint Germans,</hi> and there Judgment definitively given, ſeldom are any of the Reaſons of Condemnation mentioned in the Decree, and never any Appeal or Reviſion admitted of; ſo at laſt it was untill the <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>June</hi> laſt, and whether this be the tenderneſs, or the Juſtice which is mentioned, we do not know, but we are well aſſured, that the Methods of your Majeſty's Clemency and Juſtice on like occaſions have been far otherwiſe; and we appeal to the preſent Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, Monſieur <hi>Courtin,</hi> if almoſt in all Caſes that he or any of the Ambaſſadours thought fit to own when his Excellency was here before, and your Majeſty in War with <hi>Holland,</hi> ſeizing many Ships as Prize, and under great ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion claimed by the <hi>French,</hi> whether it were not very cuſtomary to have a ſhort reference, and a Summary Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of all Papers by the Judge of the Admiralty in his Chamber; and that if any thing appeared fair in the Caſe, whether the Ships were not immediately releas't with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Law, charge, or delay; and 'twill not be out of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, we hope, to annex hereunto the Copy of an Order of the 22. of <hi>July</hi> 1665. ſigned by the then Lords Commiſſioners of Prizes, where it will appear that eighteen <hi>French</hi> Ships which were laden with Wine and Brandy, being at <hi>Dover,</hi> and detained as Prize, were all eighteen by one Order diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged without any Law, or even the Ceremony of the Judge's
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41002:25"/>
Examination, being ſingly on the Credit of the mba Aſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor's Word, affirming that they belonged unto the <hi>French.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>As for the matter of Reviſions or Appeals after Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the Court of Admiralty here, we know his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency will alſo remember, That never any Man was deny'd his Liberty therein; but on the contrary, your Majeſty gave a ſtanding Commiſſion for Appeals in all Caſes of Prizes, and fill'd it with the Lords of your Council only, that every Caſe might receive a candid as well as unqueſtionable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination.</p>
                              <p>We might alſo put your Majeſty in mind, That during the whole Term of your late League with <hi>France,</hi> when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any <hi>French</hi> Ships were ſeized by the <hi>Hollander,</hi> and afterwards retaken by his Majeſty's Frigats, ſuch <hi>French</hi> Ships were always reſtor'd on Demand, no conſideration being had of the time they were in poſſeſſion of the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander,</hi> whether a Month, two, or three, as ſometimes they were; and when the <hi>French</hi> owner, as it hath happened, knew not of ſuch retaking, but that the Ship was according to Law condemned to your Majeſty, and ſold with other Prizes; yet the Claimer appearing, your Majeſty, hath ordered the Mony and product of the Ships to be reſtored unto him.</p>
                              <p>Such various Methods of Juſtice and of Clemency might have intituled your Majeſty to a different acknowledgment, and more advantageous Effects.</p>
                              <p>As to the other part of the ſaid Paper, it ſeems to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain very harſh Imputations on the Trade of your Majeſty's Subjects, and from ſome ill Practice perhaps found out (as every where there may be Inſtances of the like) General Rules are made, and ſevere Impreſſions taken, which having entered the thoughts of ſome Eminent Miniſters, we muſt not wonder, how frequent and how multiplied ſoever your Majeſty's Recommendations for Juſtice are, that the events
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41002:26"/>
of Tryals prove ſo unfortunate; if your Majeſty will but vouchſafe to caſt your Eye on the Cauſes here annex'd, you will ſoon ſee,</p>
                              <p>Whether (as it is imputed) all the Ships taken are <hi>Dutch</hi>-built?</p>
                              <p>Whether they are all ſuch as never were in <hi>England?</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>Whether all the Maſters, and all the Mariners are <hi>Dutch?</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>Whether the Documents be for Perſons unknown, and often-times not named?</p>
                              <p>Whether in the whole Liſt, there be more than one Ship from <hi>Waterford,</hi> and but ſix from the reſt of all <hi>Ireland,</hi> but from <hi>Scotland</hi> not ſo much as one.</p>
                              <p>Wheher it is credible all the Ships Company do ſwear they are ſent to <hi>Holland,</hi> when ſo many are taken even coming from <hi>Holland?</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>Tour Majeſty may ſee how many Ships in the Liſt are <hi>Engliſh</hi>-built, taken with <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colours, <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>Engliſh</hi> Owners, ſome of them known to your Majeſty, and to whom the beſt Papers your Majeſty, or your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters can ſign, or the Treaties do require, are given but all in vain.</p>
                              <p>So that if the Caſe be in the general quite different from what in the general is repreſented, we hope it will be no crime for your Majeſty's Subjects to make ſome noiſe in <hi>England,</hi> when they are hurt, and when they ſee their goods taken from them by violence; and that violence rather juſtified, than redreſs'd by Law.</p>
                              <p>'Tis not for the Condemnation paſs't on theſe very ill Caſes enumerated, that your Subjects do complain, for it were to their advantage, if all ſuch were puniſh't and deterr'd from Trade who by colluſion take ſhare in that profit, which the favour of the preſent Conjucture ſeems wholy to appropriats to this Kingdom.</p>
                              <p>
                                 <pb n="51" facs="tcp:41002:26"/>And ſurely your Majeſty and the whole Kingdom did reckon upon this Advantage, and the extent of Trade that would naturally flow, as one of the greateſt Fruits and Bleſſings of your Peace; ſo that your Majeſty being ſenſible of great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay and loſs of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Trading Ships in the late War, did think it adviſable to admit your Subjects to repair them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on the ſuddain by purchaſing of Foreign Ships, and your Majeſty by your Authority made them free and fit to partake in the benefit of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships, to the diminution of thoſe higher Cuſtoms which otherwiſe ſuch Ships were obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to pay, and while your Subjects, with theſe and with their own home-built Ships, are in proſecution of the ſaid advantages, while every Man is invited by the Conjuncture to venture more, and to inlarge his Trade, while by a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral truſt in the Peace and Alliance your Majeſty holds with all your Neighbours round about, they are led to go abroad unarm'd and without defence, we cannot but lament it as a great misfortune and diſappointment, to obſerve how theſe your Majeſty's Subject are frequently made a Prey of, and very evily treated both at Sea and Land.</p>
                              <p>Wherefore conſidering that the root of all theſe Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ariſes from the Violence and Rapine of the <hi>French</hi>-Capers, who ought to be look't on as diſturbers of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick quiet, and Enemies of the good Friendſhip between the two Crowns, we are humbly of opinion that your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty has juſt occaſion from the injuries paſt, and thoſe which are now depending, and which do every day increaſe, to make a very ſerious Repreſentation of all unto his moſt <hi>Chriſtian Majeſty;</hi> and not only preſs for ſome better me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of repairing the grievances mentioned, but earneſtly to inſiſt on the calling in of all <hi>Privateers;</hi> or elſe your Majeſty muſt do right, and give defence to your Subjects
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41002:27"/>
from all the Inſolencies which they ſo frequently meet. All which is moſt humbly ſubmitted.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <dateline>Council-Chamber <date>31. <hi>July</hi> 1676.</date>
                                 </dateline>
                                 <signed>
                                    <list>
                                       <item>Angleſey,</item>
                                       <item>Bath,</item>
                                       <item>Craven,</item>
                                       <item>J. Ernle,</item>
                                       <item>Finch C.</item>
                                       <item>Bridgewater,</item>
                                       <item>H. Coventry,</item>
                                       <item>G. Cartret.</item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>Robert Southwell.</hi>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                           <div type="part">
                              <p>His Majeſty taking into his ſerious Conſideration the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Complaints of his Subjects, and having a great ſenſe and reſentment of their ill uſage, hath thought fit to approve the ſaid Report, and is therefore graciouſly pleas'd to order as it's hereby ordered accordingly.</p>
                              <p>That the Right Honourable Mr. Secretary <hi>Coventry</hi> do immediately tranſmit to his Majeſties Embaſſador at <hi>Paris</hi> a Copy thereof, that ſo the evil and the unhappy ſtate of theſe things may be made known in that Court, and the Remedies preſst for in his Majeſties Name, which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the ſaid Report; and Mr. Secretary is alſo to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſador here, with the ſame Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation, and to Expoſtulate upon all theſe Hardſhips, and the little Remedy given to his Majeſties Subjects, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the Merits of their Cauſes, or the Recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of them by his Majeſty. That ſo his Excellency be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made ſenſible of his Majeſties Diſpleaſure herein, and the reaſonable Diſcontent of his Subjects, there may be by his Care ſuch lively Impreſſions hereof fixed with the King his Maſter, and the Miniſters of <hi>France,</hi> as may redreſs the Evils that are complained of, and obtain the juſt Remedies which are propoſed.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Phillip Lloyd.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:41002:27"/>
               <p>To theſe Evidences, I might add the Liſt of ſeveral Ships belonging to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, taken by <hi>French Privateers</hi> ſince <hi>December,</hi> 1673. which was alſo preſented to the Right Honourable the <hi>Committee of his Majeſties Privy-Council for Trade;</hi> and by them to his Majeſty, together with the Names of their Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and their other Circumſtances; but it would be too copious for this place. Therefore 'tis ſufficient for me to ſhew you only an excellent Account of the Buſineſs it ſelf, and of the great Care and Pains of the Noble Lords of the Council's <hi>Committee for Trade;</hi> and of his Majeſties Royal reſentment of the Sufferings of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and the Abuſes put upon our Nation; which may teſtifie, that no Nation under Heaven can have better Reaſons on their ſide to juſtifie a War, than <hi>England</hi> hath againſt <hi>France,</hi> for the many Diſhonours, Affronts, and Injuries done us, in recompence of his Majeſties high Integrity, and fair Carriage towards them.</p>
               <p>But this Unfaithfulneſs of theirs towards us is ingraft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their very Nature, as may appear not only by what hath of late been obſerved, but alſo by the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of old, all the time that <hi>Scotland</hi> was under a Crown ſeparate from <hi>England,</hi> it having then been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually made uſe of by <hi>France,</hi> when any Difficulties were upon us, as a <hi>Back-door</hi> to enter, diſturb, weaken, and attempt us here in <hi>England.</hi> Therefore having, ſince the happy Union of the two Crowns under King <hi>James,</hi> been at a loſs all his Reign how to diſturb us by their wonted way, they at length got an Opportunity to plague us, by bolſtering up a boiſterous <hi>Presbyterian Party</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that might open the <hi>Back-door</hi> again, to let into <hi>England,</hi> not only Armies, but the delicate <hi>Pandora</hi> with her <hi>Box of Beauty,</hi> varniſh'd over with
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41002:28"/>
the name of the <hi>Holy Diſcipline,</hi> and fill'd with all the Plagues of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to make our Nation miſerable; I mean <hi>Presbytery,</hi> the pious Mother, Nurſe and Seminary of <hi>Civil Wars,</hi> and perpetual Factions among us: and thus for the planting of War here, we are beholden to <hi>France,</hi> among the other good Deeds they have done to our Nation.—But that I may no longer talk in the Clouds, the plain Story in brief is this:</p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> having long had a Deſign of Conquering the <hi>Spaniſh Low - Countrys,</hi> and conceiving it was no time to diſcover or attempt it, as long as <hi>England</hi> ſhould be in a condition to hinder it, therefore to remove this Impediment out of the way, the beſt way for attaining their End was thought to be in the firſt place an Imbroil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the King of <hi>England,</hi> that inſtead of looking to Concerns abroad, he might be held in Conteſt at home with a factious Party of his <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Subjects, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and in the year 1639. had ſhewn themſelves very vexatious and troubleſome to his Majeſties Government, about matter of <hi>Kirk - Diſcipline,</hi> and its Government by Biſhops: This was matter combuſtible enough for <hi>France</hi> to work upon, and blow into a flame: ſo that Cardinal <hi>Richlieu,</hi> grand Miniſter of State to the <hi>French</hi> King, by his Agents giving them large Promiſes and Encouragements, got into a participation of Counſels with them; whereby the Faction was agitated into a downright Rebellion there, under the Name of ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Reformation;</hi> and then followed Counſels alſo for an Invaſion of <hi>England;</hi> which was effected, and they made their way with an Army to <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> poſſeſſing themſelves of it. But by the King's Prudence they were ſent home again, a Pacification being made, and hoped it was that all would have remain'd quiet. But this ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41002:28"/>
matter not ſuiting with the mind of the <hi>French Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry,</hi> and <hi>Richlieu</hi> finding that there was a working up of the like Diſcontents, and a likelihood of the ſame Deſigns in <hi>England</hi> for the cauſe, or rather pretence of <hi>Religion,</hi> the Bellows were blown here alſo by the ſame hand; ſome of the heads of the <hi>Faction</hi> here were brought to a brotherly correſpondence of Counſels and Reſolutions with their Friends of <hi>Scotland,</hi> a conjunct Deſign was laid for a <hi>Second Invaſion</hi> upon <hi>England,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Name of <hi>Brotherly Aſſiſtance;</hi> and the Platform of the great <hi>Covenant</hi> was then propoſed, approved by the Agents of their friend <hi>Richlieu,</hi> to be ſet on foot firſt in <hi>Scotland;</hi> and by Agreement it was afterward to be handed thence in due time back into <hi>England.</hi> In the mean while, the FORTY ONE <hi>Parliament</hi> being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, matters then ripened apace for their purpoſe by means of a prevalent Faction in Parliament, which very much alarm'd the King and his Court, inſomuch that he conceived it was high time to rip open this Evil, by diſcovering, ſeizing, and accuſing ſome of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Heads of the <hi>Faction, viz.</hi> a Lord, and <hi>Five Members</hi> of the Houſe of Commons. The Articles of the Charge againſt them were in number Seven, One of which was; <hi>That They had traiterouſly invited and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged a Foreign Power to Invade his Majeſties Kingdom of England.</hi> Which was ſo true, that he deſired a Tryal of them; but their Party in the Houſe not daring to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to be put to Proof, they ſhock'd the King in the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; and ſo the Affair of the COVENANT, and the other Effects of that <hi>Invitation,</hi> ran the more roundly on to a ripeneſs and final Diſpatch in <hi>Scotland,</hi> by the time that the Sun in its courſe brought on the year 1643. And then came on a Second <hi>Invaſion</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41002:29"/>
their Colours with this Rebellious <hi>Motto,</hi> FOR THE CROWN AND COVENANT OF BOTH KINGDOMS. And thus you ſee how far we were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to <hi>France</hi> for all the Miſeries of the enſuing Wars, and the numerous Brood of Factions which iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thence in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> Of the certain Truth whereof we might have had undeniable Evidence, upon the Tryal of thoſe whom the King had then charged with Treaſon, if the Temper of that time would have permitted a fair proſecution; however, it was (I remember) ſufficiently talk't of in thoſe days; and I have now by me a Book in the <hi>French</hi> Tongue, which was printed 24 Years ago by <hi>Adrian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lac,</hi> at the <hi>Hague</hi> in <hi>Holland;</hi> in the third part whereof are eight Chapters, and over the ſecond Chapter is this Title, [<hi>Le Cardinal de Richelieu la cauſe des Deſordres arrivez en An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleterre.</hi>] That is to ſay, [<hi>Cardinal Richelieu the cauſe of the Diſorders befallen</hi> England.] Which he brought in (as I told you) by the way of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the ruin of our Peace, the Royal Family, the Church, and the whole State and Government of our Kingdom.</p>
               <p>But this tampering with and corrupting other Prince's Subjects, is an old Game that the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters have ever been playing all over <hi>Europ.</hi> Let it be remember'd how the ſame <hi>Richelieu</hi> wrought the Revolt of <hi>Portugal</hi> from the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and the Rebellion in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and carry'd on the Wars in both thoſe Countries to bring down the Power of <hi>Spain;</hi> how he tamper'd alſo with the <hi>Swede,</hi> under <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus,</hi> to invade the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire:</hi> and then with the <hi>Emperour</hi>'s General, <hi>Walleſtein,</hi> to betray the <hi>Imperial</hi> Army; by whoſe ſuddain death the <hi>French King</hi> loſt the great opportunity to work him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into a poſſeſſion of the <hi>Imperial Throne.</hi> How
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41002:29"/>
Cardinal <hi>Mazarin,</hi> after him, carried on the Popular Commotions raiſed by <hi>Maſaniello</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> by ſending thither the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> to be their Head, to the almoſt wreſting of that Kingdom out of the Hand of the <hi>Spaniard;</hi> and then alſo how he lurch't that Duke, and deſerted him: Moreover, how the laſt Year the <hi>French Intrigues</hi> ſo far prevailed in <hi>Spain,</hi> as to turn the <hi>Queen-Mother</hi> out of her Regency, drive out her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites, ſuch as ſhe thought moſt fit and firm for the young King's Safety, to put him into other Hands, and turn all things in that Court topſie-turvy, that being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated and held in play by their own diviſions at Home, they might be leſs able to have regard to the preſervation of the <hi>Flemings,</hi> or to the carrying on a Joynt-war with the <hi>Hollanders.</hi> How they have been the common Enemies of every State, deſtroying the Peace of Government every where; ſowing of Factions in all Princely Courts, their Councils, or among ſuch of the Subjects as are fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious; or elſe they jumble one Prince againſt another by turns, as they did the Prince <hi>Elector Palatine</hi> againſt the <hi>Elector of Mentz,</hi> ſtarting up an occaſion of Quarrel betwixt them; one while to take part with the <hi>Elector Palatine</hi> againſt <hi>Mentz,</hi> another while with <hi>Mentz</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Prince;</hi> whoſe Country they miſerably ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſed and waſted.</p>
               <p>It cannot be forgotten what they lately did to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the <hi>Emperor</hi>'s Council, by means of his own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite Prince <hi>Lobcowitz,</hi> whom they bought for Mony to betray his Maſter's Counſels and Affairs; beſides their Intrigue in the ſame manner with the Prince of <hi>Furſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> and his Brother. Alſo, what they did in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces</hi> to incommode his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> by bolſtering up the <hi>De Wits,</hi> and their <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venſtein</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:41002:30"/>
Republican party againſt the Princely.</p>
               <p>What they have done to clog the <hi>Emperor,</hi> by foſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Rebellion againſt him in <hi>Hungary;</hi> and how great charge they are at to ſever the power of the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and of the Duke of <hi>Hanover,</hi> from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt of the <hi>Empire</hi> in this War. How they have diverſe times indangered all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> by confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derating with the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> to diſturb both <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> and <hi>Poland;</hi> for which cauſe (as My Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> writes in his Hiſtory) the <hi>Pope</hi> had like to have given away the Title <hi>Moſt Chriſtian</hi> from their <hi>French</hi> King <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, to beſtow it upon our <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth before he had been dubb'd by his <hi>Holineſs</hi> with that of <hi>Defenſor Fidei.</hi>—What Artifices have been uſed by them to ſettle and nouriſh perpetual Faction among the <hi>Poliſh Nobility,</hi> whereby other great Opportunities have diverſe times been given the <hi>Turk</hi> to fall upon them.</p>
               <p>In a word, their common practice hath been, to give the World all manner of diſturbance, and ſo to render themſelves in its Opinion the common Enemies of its Peace, a publick Peſt among States and Princes: in every Country they either find combuſtible ſtuff, or elſe make it, and then ſet fire to it; they are at a mighty charge to find Fodder for the various Animals of Faction in all Places. By this means <hi>Divide &amp; Impera</hi> makes way for them, and thus they conquer more than by their Arms: they inflame Countries thus, as well as burn them, as they did <hi>Alſatia,</hi> that having enough to do to quench fires at Home, they may have neither leiſure nor power to hinder <hi>French Projects</hi> abroad. Queſtionleſs then, ſince we in <hi>England</hi> have ſeen and do ſee our Neighbours Houſes fired one after another, 'tis high time to look to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41002:30"/>
our own, and ſecure our ſelves and all <hi>Europ,</hi> from ſuch <hi>Boutefeus,</hi> and the ſad Effects of their Impious Courſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECTION IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That as the French have dealt falſly with us, and all other Princes in the point of Peace; There is no Security to be had for any one Party, but by a Joynt War.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HIs Majeſty of <hi>England</hi> having hitherto on his part preſerved a fair Reſpect and Amity towards <hi>France,</hi> paſſing by the many Indignities and Injuries done to himſelf and his Nation, in hope his Patience might, by fair means, have prevail'd with the <hi>French</hi> King at length to do reaſon to us, and the reſt of his Neighbours; and that to that end his Majeſty might have perſwaded him to have forborn a further proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the War in <hi>Flanders,</hi> that thereby we might have ſeen ſome good Fruit of his Majeſties friendly interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing in order to the procurement of a ſpeedy Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and the <hi>French</hi> pretending ſo to do, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his Majeſty to a performing the good Office of Mediation betwixt <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>Confederates;</hi> but now the Iſſue of all being contrary, for that the <hi>French</hi> have made an unexpected ſudden Breach further upon <hi>Flanders</hi> in the depth of this Winter, and appear'd reſolute to carry the whole Country, if they could, before Spring; ſo that this ſurpriſe gave a new Alarm to us and all the Neighbours: the World muſt juſtifie his Majeſty, it after all amicable means uſed in vain, he ſhall now find
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41002:31"/>
himſelf in prudence concern'd to take a Courſe by War, to vindicate his own Honour againſt the many Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Affronts acted by <hi>France;</hi> and by God's bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to become the happy Inſtrument to recover the Rights of the oppreſſed States and Princes; as alſo to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his own Nation againſt the Dangers threatned at our very doors, and to reſtore unto the Generality that glorious Chriſtian Peace, which cannot otherwiſe be obtained.</p>
               <p>Peace was the Subject of Chriſt's laſt Sermon; the great Legacy that he bequeathed to his Followers. What Chriſtians then are they, that make it their Intereſt and Buſineſs to deſtroy it on Earth! This is the Work of wild Beaſts and Monſters to infeſt whole Countries; and when men act as ſuch, the very <hi>Law of Nature</hi> as well as of Nations, excites and juſtifies all Mankind to War againſt them: Look back on the former <hi>Sections</hi> of this Diſcourſe, and there you have a ſight who are the men, whom no Treaties nor Intreaties can reduce to a more <hi>Chriſtian State.</hi> Their <hi>Motto</hi> is, <hi>Jus eſt in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, No Law but the Law of Arms:</hi> therefore by Arms alone the Quarrel is to be decided; and that for theſe following Reaſons: <hi>Provided</hi> that <hi>Foreign States</hi> and their Miniſters do not trifle with, but come up round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to us: And that people here at home do their Duty for Encouragement anſwerable to the Importance of ſo great and neceſſary an undertaking. Which (no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) every man wiſe and honeſt will be ready to do, and no reaſonable man can doubt it, ſeeing our own and the Univerſal Intereſt now calls for it, and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament did this laſt Summer ſo earneſtly addreſs for it; and (I ſuppoſe) his Majeſty had ſuitably anſwer'd it, had he conceived the Time to be ſeaſonable, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41002:31"/>
ſome other Circumſtances agreeable; which the Law moſt prudently hath left in his own Judgment to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; the more full and better ſence whereof may be collected out of his Anſwer to the <hi>Addreſs</hi> it ſelf; at the end whereof I read this Intimation; <hi>That he could not do things for the ſecurity of his People, with thoſe Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to them, which by the</hi> Parliament'<hi>s Aſſiſtance at that time he might have done.</hi> Which (I remember very well) moſt Men did interpret to be meant of the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> not granting, and the King's wanting the <hi>Six hundred thouſand pounds</hi> demanded by his Majeſty for a further ſupply, which might have enabled him to, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But of this, more anon.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Here are the Reaſons afore-mentioned.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. The firſt Reaſon for War againſt them, I draw from the <hi>Summum probabile,</hi> the Higheſt probability, that if we help not to reduce them, and extinguiſh War abroad, they will at laſt bring it home to us. Which I prove by conſideration of theſe three particulars.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>France</hi>'s Aphoriſms of State.</item>
                     <item>The <hi>Political Creed.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Their Neceſſity to continue in War.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>1. The firſt <hi>Aphoriſm</hi> is ſuch as is deſtructive of Peace in all Places, and diſpoſes them to act accordingly. That is, <hi>To enter into all ſorts of Affairs by Right or by wrong, by Hook or by Crook,</hi> and every where to become <hi>Arbiters</hi> by <hi>Violence</hi> or by <hi>Cunning,</hi> by <hi>Threats</hi> or by <hi>Friendly Pretences.</hi> In all the Differences paſt or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, they ſome way or other wind themſelves in to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41002:32"/>
take party, and form for themſelves an Intereſt: nor did ever any People ſhew the leaſt diſlike to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and an Inclination to Rebellion, but the <hi>French</hi> fomented it, and made the Factions their <hi>Allies.</hi> They never entred into any War to favour any Party, but with intent to exaſperate it; nor into any Peace, but to ſow the Seeds of New Diſputes, as paſt Experience hath made evident, and the Stories of theſe Truths afford nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Examples; but I now want room to inſert them: So that if we conſtrain them to Peace, it will laſt no longer than they can work our Mal-contents into Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny, and then they will violate that Peace by encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging them, or by ſiding with them, ſecretly or openly.</p>
                  <p>2. A <hi>Second Aphoriſm</hi> is, to have for their only Rule <hi>Intereſt of State;</hi> ſo that the <hi>Faith of Treaties,</hi> the <hi>Good of Religion,</hi> or the <hi>Ties of Blood and Amity cannot hold</hi> them. The Inſtances for proof thereof I have given already. All that the <hi>Turks</hi> have done in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> ſince the time of <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt to our time, they owe to the Alliances of <hi>France</hi> with the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Court; and to the diverſion which <hi>France</hi> made in their Favour, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any <hi>Chriſtians</hi> who were likely to act againſt that Common Enemy of our <hi>Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. Their <hi>Third Aphoriſm</hi> is, <hi>To keep other States,</hi> as much as they can, <hi>divided and buſied at home, or elſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in ſome External War,</hi> as <hi>England, Germany, Italy, Denmark, Spain, Poland, Holland,</hi> and many other Countries have had ſad Experience. What Peace then with ſuch a Nation, when her Witchcrafts are ſo many?</p>
                  <p>Their Fourth is, <hi>To keep their Younger Brothers of the beſt Families alwaies in Arms abroad at the Expence of their Neighbours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:41002:32"/>All theſe are the <hi>Maxims</hi> of <hi>Conquerors;</hi> infallible Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of a profound Deſign to be proſecuted to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Bounds of Conqueſt: So that to talk to them of Peace, is to talk againſt their <hi>Intereſt;</hi> that is, 'tis to no purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>The other thing to be conſidered, is their <hi>Political Creed;</hi> which I ſhall not give you in my own words, but as it is tranſlated, having been printed in the <hi>French</hi> Tongue at <hi>Ville-Franche by Jean Petit,</hi> 1677.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="poltical_creed">
                              <p>
                                 <hi>[They believe that what others call Violence, is but a bare precaution, and a purſuit of one of their Infallible Rules of Art,</hi> viz. <hi>That Conquerors ought to provide for the future, by deſtroying whatever may hurt them, and that they ought to have no Law but the Sword, the Appetite of Governing, and the Glory to be had by aggrandizing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at the coſt of their Neighbours.</hi> Pyrrhus <hi>alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved this juſt; and</hi> Caeſar, <hi>that all things were lawful for Dominion.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>They generally applaud theſe</hi> Maxims; <hi>and hold that nothing is forbid to them, that may diſturb their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and ſow diviſion among them: that they have a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret joy in doing wrong, and whatever elſe may be moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting and outrageous. That Pity is a cowardly Vertue which over-throws a Crown, whoſe beſt Support is Fear, and Impiety its Foundation. That Arms inſpire a reverence among Men, and Troops are the admirable Advocates which plead a cauſe beſt. That the proclamation of the Cannon is above all other Titles. That Juſtice is a Phantaſm; Reaſon a Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera; Marriage a trifle; the Faith of Treaties an illuſion; Peace but a bait. That their Cabals ought to be full of myſtery, their Conferences inſnaring, and their Oaths but ſport of Children, a Trap to catch a Cully, and a Charm for Fools.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <pb n="64" facs="tcp:41002:33"/>
                                 <hi>They further believe and ſay, That Perjury is juſt, and that according to their new Morals, Ill may be done for a greater Good. That ſincerity ruins them, that perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is profitable; Impoſture, of much benefit; that Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is the Charter of a Prince: Faith, a fooliſh Maxim; Keeping their Word but a mean Complyance; and Violence the proper hinge to move upon.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Our Tears are their Tipple, our Sighs they regard not; they ſpeak one thing, do another; make great Promiſes, never perform any: Their Mouth flatters, while their Heart betrays; they have no Friendſhip without an End; Vengeance is ſweet to them, their Protection heavy: They embrace with one Arm, and ſmother with another:</hi> France <hi>is the</hi> Proteus <hi>of the Age, and hath a thouſand Faces; She enters like a Lamb, transforms into the Fox, and thence becomes a devouring Wolf. They never pardon, are never to be ſurpriſed, and their Ways are paſt finding out: A double face, a charming Voice, with a ſtudied behaviour. They count nothing a pleaſure but what tends to enſlave the People, and lead them to deſpair.</hi> Tunc oderint dum metuant; <hi>and they ſcoff at the hatred of the conquered, if they can but make them fear.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>Elizabeth <hi>of</hi> England <hi>always aſſerted, That</hi> France <hi>might be eſpouſed as a Friend, but never approved for a Neighbour; their rapidity and heat conſuming what they can reach, not being able to ſubſiſt without coveting and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading their Neighbours Goods and Territories.</hi>]</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>The laſt of the three Particulars to be conſidered, is, That <hi>France is under a neceſſity to continue War as long as they can.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1. This appears by what I have hinted in the <hi>Third Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: viz.</hi> That their King having brought the younger Brothers of his Nobility and Gentry (which are a vaſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41002:33"/>
number) to depend upon War for a Livelihood, and by War for a making of their Fortunes; ſo that he hath made War their Trade. 'Tis abſurd to imagine he will by any long Obſervation of Peace deſtroy their Trade and Livelihood: For then, what follows? They muſt even prey upon himſelf at home; he muſt maintain them, or they mutiny, and turn popular, and the common people being eaſily to be agitated with the hope of eaſing their moſt intolerable Burthens (for whoever among the <hi>Bourgeois,</hi> the Tradeſmen, or the Peaſants, do get either Lands or Pence, their King, as oft as he pleaſes, demands three parts in four, and ſo they pay him three Farthings of every Penny, if he Tax it upon them, and ſends Troops of Horſe to collect it; as now they do at this time in the Provinces of their own Nation; as I have ſeen the Account of it ſet down in a Letter which came to hand but few hours ago) for theſe things, I ſay, may readily diſpoſe them to cloſe with mal-content <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in War,</hi> who will be ſure to drive that Trade of War at home, if they have it not abroad. This alone is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence enough to ſhew he muſt needs avoid a Peace, though he may ſeem willing to Treat about it, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend fair towards it, and perhaps keep it a little while, till he can frame to himſelf greater Advantages by breaking it; which his Intereſt (you ſee) will compel him to, to avoid that <hi>grand domeſtick</hi> Miſchief aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
                  <p>2. Beſides, Peace is ſo far againſt his Intereſt, that if he grant it, he cannot have any tolerable pretence to keep up that vaſt Revenue, which he raiſes at preſent out of the Purſe of the people to maintain his Wars; which I have heard to amount yearly to above <hi>Eleven Millions of Pounds Sterling,</hi> beſides his <hi>Contributions</hi>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:41002:34"/>
raiſed out of conquer'd Countries, which are eſtimated at a grand rate by thoſe that underſtand them: and all theſe muſt needs be diminiſhed if he permit Peace. So that 'tis a mean thought, to imagin that the <hi>French Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> ſhould not ſee and avoid theſe Conſequences, which would leſſen their Profit, as well as their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. To be brief, By another <hi>Reaſon of State</hi> he is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated not to permit Peace long, becauſe without War they cannot long retain their numerous Princes, Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chals, Dukes, and chief Nobility, in a dependence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Crown for augmentation of their Eſtates, or the ſatisfaction of their Pride, Ambition, and Avarice, which is not otherwiſe to be done, but by having to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow on them great Military Commands, Offices, and Governments in the Conquer'd, and other Conquerable Places. By theſe things you ſee what Neceſſity lies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their <hi>Miniſters</hi> to adviſe and determine, as Monſieur <hi>Louvoy,</hi> one of the chief among them very lately did; that there was a neceſſity for their continuation of War. And indeed, No man better than <hi>Louvoy</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the Temper, Inclination, Sence, and Intereſt of his <hi>Maſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now if theſe things be ſo, 'tis time for us to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed with our other Arguments for War, on our behalf and foreign Neighbours: one of which I have already gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. A <hi>Second Reaſon,</hi> or <hi>Argument</hi> for us and them to War againſt <hi>France,</hi> is; That as the <hi>French Miniſters</hi> cannot admit Peace, ſo this is one evident Token they never intended it; foraſmuch as they ſo order'd the matter of Peace under debate at <hi>Nimiguen,</hi> that the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was rendred hopeleſs.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:41002:34"/>III. They have hitherto fruſtrated the gracious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, Offertures, and Endeavours of his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> to procure a Peace by <hi>Mediation</hi> on the behalf of the <hi>Confederates,</hi> and all <hi>Europ:</hi> which is no leſs than a tacit Declaration for an Univerſal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. A Fourth <hi>Reaſon</hi> may be drawn from the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of <hi>France,</hi> which is reſtleſs, and boundleſs; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be ſatisfied more than is their Avarice, large e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſwallow All upon the Continent, while they reſerve theſe Iſles of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> as the laſt Morſels.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. A Fifth <hi>Reaſon,</hi> had I time or place here, might be copiouſly drawn from the huge magnitude of <hi>France,</hi> its Dominion being extended upon the ruins of other Nations to an immenſe Bulk, beyond all tolerable Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance: ſo that in compariſon with them and their Mountain of Power and Greatneſs, the Neighbour States and Princes are become ſo light, that they are but as the <hi>ſmall Duſt in the Ballance.</hi> And therefore unleſs a Courſe be taken to give them a Diminution, there will ere long be very little probability of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to give him a <hi>Counterpoiſe.</hi> That excellent Prince the Duke of <hi>Rohan,</hi> in his little, but weighty Book, ſtating the Intereſts of ſeveral Princes, deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines it is the Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> to keep ſuch a Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of their Powers, as not to permit that either of them grow ſo great as to be able to oppreſs another: And that we ought ever to hold it even betwixt <hi>France</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and if either of them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, to reduce it to an Equality; this was accounted a principal part of the Ancient Grandeur of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Nation: King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth firſt well ſetled it
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41002:35"/>
in managing the Differences betwixt <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, then both Emperor and King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt King of <hi>France,</hi> the two Grand Competitors of that Age. That excellent Princeſs Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> well improved it, and ſo it continued till the time of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> who firſt erred in this matter of Publick Intereſt, to ſerve his own private, by greatning of <hi>France</hi> beyond due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, ſo that he interpoſed the Difficulties which ſince lay in the way of Reducing it. By the Influence of this old piece of policy, it was that <hi>England</hi> was always in a condition, whenſoever ſhe pleaſed, to diſpence <hi>Peace,</hi> or <hi>War</hi> to every Nation, and thereby great Honour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounded to our own, throughout the World, and there is nothing but War can reſtore it, by curing the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grown Dropſie of the <hi>French</hi> Greatneſs.</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. You had before an Intimation of another moſt conſiderable Reaſon, drawn from a conſideration that no Peace that can be made, can give us any ſecurity of enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it long; to which I may add, That a <hi>Peace</hi> will but betray us to the next Opportunity the <hi>French</hi> ſhall pleaſe to take. Beſides, in the interval we ſhould but give him the opportunity to reinforce himſelf, ramaſs his Treaſury, and thereby inable himſelf to proſecute the old <hi>Artifice</hi> of corrupting other Princes, Miniſters, Officers and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, and work his Ends ſo as to alienate and ſeparate as many of the Conſederates as he can from their hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Counſels in common for Mutuall preſervation, to embrace ſuch terms as he ſhall, under a ſpecious ſhew of Advantages, think fit to propoſe unto them; which if obtained, would utterly break them one after another, and induce this Inconveniency upon <hi>England,</hi> to be left alone, or with but few Participants to joyn in the Work of Reducing <hi>France</hi> into its former legitimate moderate Condition.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:41002:35"/>VII. Another Reaſon is to be derived from a Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the great increaſe of the Naval Power of <hi>France,</hi> whereby they are enboldened to give diſturbance to our Merchant-men in our own Seas; ſuch an Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to his Majeſty, and Violation of our Rights by Sea, as is not to be indured; and which the Kings of this Iſland have from all Antiquity poſſeſſed as far as the very ſhores of <hi>France,</hi> excluſive of any Pretentions of Right of any other Nations within the FOUR SEAS: The Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences whereof were collected, and with Arguments drawn from all ſorts of Learning and Records, digeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into one excellent Book, by that moſt famous Man Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> entituled <hi>MARECLA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</hi> Among the particulars whereof I remember that the Addition of the <hi>Port-Cullis</hi> to the Royal Badges of the Crown of <hi>England</hi> (which is yet to be ſeen upon many of the Royal Houſes built by our Kings) was made for this Reaſon, even to ſignifie to all the World, That we had a juſt Right and Title, at pleaſure to ſhut up, and open the Sea when we thought fit, as it were, with a <hi>Port-Cullis,</hi> to all Paſſengers paſſing by Sea. And by the ſame Evidences it is there proved, that our Title to our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in the Sea is as good as any Title the <hi>French</hi> King hath to any part of his Dominion by Land. His Grand-Father wrote divers Letters with his own Hand to King <hi>James</hi> (which I have formerly ſeen in the <hi>Paper-Office</hi> at <hi>White-Hall</hi>) to ask Leave for ſome few Veſſels to fiſh for <hi>Soales</hi> (as he ſhould have occaſion) for his own Table: Which was a ſufficient Acknowledgment where the Soveraignty lies by Sea. There have been alſo, in former time, brisk Meſſengers ſent to the <hi>French</hi> Kings, requiring them, as ſoon as they had but begun to lay the Carcaſs of ſome pitiful Ship upon the Stocks,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41002:36"/>
to forbear building. Which ſhews the preſent Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of the <hi>French</hi> in making ſo grand Naval Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations to invade our Seas: And our Honour, as well as our Right, calls aloud for a Vindication.</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. There is Reaſon alſo to be drawn from a Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the hazard of Religion. 1. As concerning the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> about which I ſhall not uſe any more words to clear this point, than this ſhort Proverb now uſed in <hi>France,</hi> and by them attributed to their own King; <hi>That his Grand-Father loved the Proteſtants, his Father feared them, and he himſelf hated them.</hi> Which any one that beholds the Ruines of their demoliſhed Churches, and the hard Conditions under which they are oppreſſed in every point, within that Kingdom (too large here to recite) will eaſily believe. 2. As touching the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Religion, how that is like to fare, may readily be prognoſticated;</p>
                  <q>Tros, Rutilúſve fuat, nullo diſcrimine habebunt.</q>
                  <p>Be a <hi>Papiſt</hi> or be a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> make no difference in uſage, whereſoever they come. Witneſs to this how they have dealt in <hi>Catalonia, Alſatia,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh Low-Countrys,</hi> and divers other <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Countrys where all men exclaim againſt the Domination of <hi>France.</hi> 3. Whereas it was of old a Doctrine inſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into the minds of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> by their <hi>Father-Confeſſors,</hi> that they ought to adhere to <hi>Spain</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> rather than to promote the <hi>French</hi> Empire, becauſe <hi>Spain</hi> being then much the greater Kingdom, and eſteemed the dearer Son of the Church, by reaſon of its greater Zeal, and more ſtrict and intire Imbracement of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith, and through the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41002:36"/>
of the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> kept without any mixture of that which they call <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and therefore more likely to continue firm to the <hi>Roman See;</hi> now of later time, the State of Empire being altered, <hi>Spain</hi> brought much lower, and not able to give ſuch Protection and Defence as formerly to the <hi>Roman</hi> Cauſe in theſe parts of the World, the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are ſo far altered too, that having ſince ſeen the <hi>French</hi> go on like Conquerers, they have quitted the former Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons on <hi>Spain</hi>'s ſide, and like the Men of the World, are turned <hi>Courtiers of Fortune,</hi> crying up <hi>France</hi> altogether now, though if they pleaſe to remember how not many Years ago <hi>France,</hi> upon a petty Quarrel in <hi>Rome,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ſome of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Souldiers and the Duke of <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui</hi>'s Servants (then Ambaſſador there) ruffled the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf with ſuch unheard of Inſolence, that for meer fear he was conſtrained to abandon divers of his Friends and Kindred, and to the perpetual diſgrace of the <hi>Holy-Chair,</hi> and of their Religion, and of the Adored-Father of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> (as they would ſeem to repute him) they made him cry like a Child, and erect a Pillar in <hi>Rome,</hi> with an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, ſignifying the pretended Affront to <hi>France,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven upon it; and it continued ſome Years ſtanding, till the Tears of his <hi>Holineſs</hi> prevailed for the demoliſhing of it. Notwithſtanding all this (I ſay) the <hi>Roman Prieſts</hi> do venture to magnifie <hi>France</hi> as much as they did <hi>Spain</hi> before, not conſidering how their <hi>Intereſt of Religion</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines there by the marvelous increaſe of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Janſeniſts,</hi> and by the indifferency of zeal in moſt of the <hi>French Papiſts;</hi> and, were it not mere <hi>Reaſon of State</hi> that holds it up there among the <hi>Great Ones</hi> for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, no Man knows how ſoon it might be relinquiſh't, if a little time ſhould happen to alter that <hi>Reaſon of State,</hi> it
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41002:37"/>
being a voluble thing, if their <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſhall think they have as good reaſon to invade <hi>Italy,</hi> as other Places, and after Conqueſt of the ſmaller Princes there, to ſeize <hi>Saint Peters</hi> fair Patrimony for an Addition to the <hi>French</hi> Kings Revenue, and then make the <hi>Pope</hi> content to become his Chaplain, and to be glad of a Penſion, as the <hi>Mufti</hi> is at <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> who knows then how far Reaſon of State may alter it ſelf, and make further Alterations? But let the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Party look to that: They may hope the beſt, if they pleaſe; but we and all the reſt of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Party in <hi>Germany</hi> and other parts, muſt be ſure to go to wrack as faſt as they can reach us, and then deal with us, as they do with their own, in the Concerns of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as well as Eſtates.</p>
                  <p>Ours ſhall be ſure to go down: and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> cannot be ſure their Religion ſhall not receive Alterations; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in Secular Advantages of Wealth and Power, ſeeing even in <hi>France</hi> the King hath already converted to his own uſe a great part of the Monaſtick Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues. Therefore it almoſt equally concerns both <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> in reference to Religion, to adventure their diſtinct Powers and Intereſts in one common Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, and Reſolution, to War with him, and to hinder the obſtinate purſuit of that Project of an <hi>Univerſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">IX. The laſt Argument that might be brought is the <hi>Univerſal Inclination</hi> of our People towards a War with <hi>France.</hi> And the like Inclination, yea, and Neceſſity that appears among our Foreign Neighbours: Never was there a more marvelous Conſent of Mankind about any one Buſineſs; therefore I need not uſe more words to preſs it on.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:41002:37"/>
               <head>SECTION V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>An Account of ſuch Objections and Impediments as by Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents may be caſt in the way, in caſe His Majeſty ſhall ſee Cauſe now to make a War.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THat there are Diſcontents among us, is a thing in no wiſe to be denied; and the Authors of them are ſufficiently known. They are a ſort of ominous Birds always hovering about City and Suburbs, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming to miſrepreſent, argue, and arbitrate the great Affairs of State; and ſuch is the licentious Liberty they take to themſelves, that they cenſure, arraign, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn what and whom they pleaſe. Ever againſt the Sitting of Parliament, they gather and appear in whole Flights and Flocks, breeding of falſe News, and boding Miſchief whereſoever they come. They ſometimes haunt the Houſes of Ambaſſadors, and other Foreign Miniſters, if they can get any intimacy with their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, with whom they give, and take Supplies toward a Stock of Intelligence; the one to furniſh the Foreign Poſt, the other the <hi>Coffee-Houſes,</hi> whence they iſſue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and make ſallies upon the <hi>Canary Cabals</hi> at the <hi>Globe,</hi> the <hi>Horn,</hi> the <hi>Kings-head,</hi> or the <hi>Devil,</hi> to furniſh them, and ſettle Correſpondencies both <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi> and to that end receive Commiſſion to become <hi>Emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> and <hi>Trotters</hi> betwixt ſome particular <hi>Wiſeacres</hi> in both the <hi>Climates.</hi> If the Parliament chance at any time to be Prorogued or Adjourn'd, that Seaſon proves to this ſort of <hi>News-mongers,</hi> like a <hi>nipping Froſt</hi> to <hi>Flies,</hi> and they are even ready to die away like fainting <hi>Graſs-hoppers.</hi> There's nothing revives them in the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41002:38"/>
Interval, like ſome unlucky Miſchief befal'n the Court. 'Tis Miſchief they gape for; and yet are but Fools at doing it, and therefore ought to be better inſtructed.</p>
               <p>For if I loved Miſchief, and meant to do it, I would firſt raiſe Objections to prevent a War now, though a while ago I wiſhed well to all thoſe that had a deſire to promote it. I would object, that it is too late to enter upon it now, becauſe it ſhould a been done laſt Summer, before the <hi>French</hi> King could a made his late Impreſſion ſo far into the <hi>Spaniſh Low-Countrys,</hi> and before the <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates</hi> were brought ſo low. Beſides, I would not give way with patience, to hear another man anſwer me, that it is not too late; but prove that had his Majeſty conſented to it laſt Summer, there are moſt ſufficient Reaſons to be given why it might have turned very much to the prejudice of his Affairs; as for Inſtance,</p>
               <p>1. Had he then declared an immediate Conſent to it, it had been all one as to have declared a War; for, the <hi>French</hi> are not ſo ſlow-witted as not to apprehend it ſo, nor ſo remiſs as to neglect a dealing with us accordingly. What could we have expected, but that our Merchants Ships, which at that time were in great numbers trad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within the Dominions of <hi>France,</hi> would have been immediately ſeized, and all their Effects, which amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a vaſt ſum of mony? whereby our King, beſides the loſſes of the Merchants, muſt have loſt a great ſum of mony accruing here to his Cuſtoms by the Import of thoſe Goods and Commodities.</p>
               <p>2. His Majeſty very well underſtands what an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Point 'tis to conſent to a War, which is all one in effect as to proclaim a War, before competent prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made for it by Mony, Ammunition and Men, Ships, and all other neceſſaries for War could be ready to put it in execution.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:41002:38"/>3. The <hi>French King</hi> might then (for ought that can be ſaid to the contrary) have been thereby ſo exaſperated, as to lay aſide a while his Affairs in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and being ready furniſht with all the neceſſaries that we wanted, immediately have reſolved to fall upon us by an Invaſion; and what (I pray you) could have hindered at that time ſuch a Surpriſe of us?</p>
               <p>4. It had been a ſtrange Adventure to have been ſo forward to have engaged our ſelves by promiſe to enter into the War, before it was known what the <hi>Confederates</hi> would do towards it, to encourage us to their Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. The preſent Diſtreſs lies upon them more than upon us; therefore there ought to be no bogling with us, or delaying, but a quick doing what is reaſonable for them on their part, to engage us in their Confederacie.</p>
               <p>5. The <hi>French King,</hi> having pretended fair for an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing of His Majeſties Mediation in order to a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Peace, it was queſtionleſs very convenient we ſhould ſtop a while to ſee what would be the iſſue of his pretence, that in caſe he ſhould play foul, and deceive us, we might have the juſter and fairer cauſe to War with him.</p>
               <p>6. If there had not been any of theſe Reaſons for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay; yet the happy <hi>Alliance</hi> with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> having been ſince accompliſhed; and being a very good expedient to open the way for a more convenient en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into Confederation, is that which may abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerve to balance any pretended inconvenience of the delay of entrance.—But to proceed</p>
               <p>Moreover, If notwithſtanding theſe Reaſons, any one of thoſe men of Intelligence ſhould yet miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly <hi>Object,</hi> That laſt Summers delay hath been the ruine of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and made the recovery of it in a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41002:39"/>
manner impoſſible, and ſhould endeavour to perſwade others 'tis ſo, becauſe of the loſs of ſome few Towns there ſince, let ſuch conſider, that the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> by his not cloſing yet with us in our friendly Inclination, ſeems not to be of their Opinion, or that <hi>Flanders</hi> is yet ſo near ruine, ſeeing that he himſelf hath made a further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, by not coming up to our reaſonable Demands at this time, whenas he hath of late ſo much pretended it, and all men expected he would accordingly have done it out of hand.</p>
               <p>Beſides, Let thoſe <hi>News-and-Miſchief-Mongers</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, it is not long ago ſince they themſelves, in one of the <hi>Canary-Clubs,</hi> were of a mind, that the <hi>Confederates,</hi> if we were joyned with them, would be able to work Miracles in <hi>Flanders</hi> againſt the <hi>French:</hi> but it now ſeems that the loſs of St. <hi>Ghiſlain,</hi> or of a Town or two more, hath in a moment deprived us and the <hi>Flemmings</hi> of all Power to do what is fit to preſerve the Country. It hath been told me, that very lately, the like Diſcourſe being boldly bandied at a certain Cable of <hi>Coffee-mongers,</hi> one that ſate ſmoking hard by in a Corner of the Room, ſtept in, and ſaid honeſtly, <hi>That he wonder'd there ſhould happen among ſome men ſuch a ſudden Change of Opinion; and that it muſt needs give a ſuſpicion there is ſome invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Spring that moves them; ſome</hi> Secret Intrigue <hi>and</hi> Reſerve <hi>in the Heart, when the Tongues go at ſo rolling a rate: and that they are a ſort of people tutor'd to this Tune, to argue</hi> Pro <hi>and</hi> Con <hi>by Turns, as their own Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions alter; That they are reſolved to diſlike whatſoever the King may judge is reaſon for him next to do in his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Affairs; and that they put on the approbations and diſapprovements of a War, according as they are influenced, and as the</hi> WORD <hi>is given out by their envious Mal-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:41002:39"/>
Leaders; <hi>and as it may ſerve to pleaſe, or irritats, and to render themſelves gracious in their eyes unto whom they are Retainers. I do remember</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>what Joy the People had, and Bonfires, as ſoon as the Marriage of the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>was declared; and not many days after, this ſort of</hi> frequent Changelings <hi>raiſed I know not how many Scandals about it. How far the</hi> French <hi>have had an influence on ſuch</hi> petulant Talkers, <hi>I cannot ſay; but other men more honeſt ſpeak broad enough about it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which having been thus roundly utter'd, the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> laid down his Pipe, paid for his Diſh of <hi>Coffee,</hi> and went his way, leaving them all in an amaze to gueſs who this Man ſhould be.</p>
               <p>Now, no ſooner was this Gentleman gone, but an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, who over-heard the Diſcourſe, drew near to them; (for all are free over a <hi>Coffee-diſh</hi>) and ſitting down, ſaid, <hi>Gentlemen, pardon me if I tell you I was here t'other day, and heard ſome others of you diſcourſing about Money to carry on the War; and methought it was much any among you ſhould think it reaſonable, and moſt neceſſary to have War; and others yet be of opinion, That the Point of Money ſhould be cumber'd with Delays or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes about it. What would the Event of this be? Would it not render us ridiculous to the</hi> French, <hi>and make them ſcorn us? Would it not diſhearten the Confederates, and make them jealous, that whatſoever</hi> Reſolutions <hi>we take to give them hope of aſſiſtance, yet as ſoon as they are taken, they will by one Accident or other be made impracticable? In time of Neceſſity, and when</hi> Hannibal <hi>was at the Gates, or any other Enemy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>nigh coming, the</hi> Romans <hi>ever inſtituted a</hi> Temporary <hi>Officer, whom they called</hi> Dictator, <hi>and to him the Senate and People gave, during the publick danger, but not longer, as full Power as the King of</hi> France <hi>now enjoys, to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41002:40"/>
do and take whatſoever he ſhould judge neceſſary to ſecure the Publick State of the Nation: by which Policy they avoided all Diſputes and Debates about the Concerns of the War; and ſo they generally came off with Succeſs. Be it far from me to urge at this time, that we ſhould in this occaſion of ours imitate them, but yet methinks we ſhould ſo far learn of them, as to do all we can to avoid and lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide diſputings; eſpecially about the very</hi> Life <hi>and</hi> Sinews <hi>of a War, conſtant ſupply of Moneys, and other Neceſſaries; and to come as near the</hi> Roman <hi>Policy as the publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, convenience, and State of our Government can poſſibly permit, if we mean to obtain the like happy Succeſs. A truſt muſt be lodged ſome where; therefore 'tis beſt and ſafeſt to place it where, and in what manner the Law hath placed it. The Law obliges the People, as well as the</hi> King: <hi>It obliges the</hi> King <hi>to make War, where, and when he ſhall judge it needful. And on the other hand, it ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges the People, readily and cheerfully to give him neceſſary ſupplies; otherwiſe this abſurdity would be implied in our Law, that it ſhould oblige the King, and leave the People looſe in this matter; which can by no means be ſuppoſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then it would oblige him to an Impoſſibility; it being impoſſible for him to do his part, unleſs they on their part ſhall ſufficiently ſupply him. Which 'tis not to be imagined the People can be ſo mad as to decline, becauſe 'tis for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Safety,</hi> The Supreme Law, <hi>which is a further Tie upon them; and if they obſerve not that, it is not only to be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ends of Gubernation, but in effect a Fruſtrating both of Law and Government it ſelf: and at this time, an unnatural abandoning of our ſelves, and a giving up of that moſt noble cauſe wherein whole</hi> Europ <hi>is ſo deeply concerned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I thought,</hi> Gentlemen, <hi>to have ſpoken no more at this time; but (craving your Pardon) pray,</hi> Sirs, <hi>let me tell
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41002:40"/>
you, I over-heard alſo here t'other day, what ſome of your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſaid, reflecting upon ſome State-Particulars paſt, the reviving whereof would better become the mouth of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy, than a true</hi> Engliſh-man, <hi>being matters alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether Foreign to the Buſineſs of War, which is now The</hi> Unum Neceſſarium, <hi>The one Thing Neceſſary: and till all fit Reſolutions upon that be taken, why ſhould any matters inferiour, that may cauſe diſcontent or diviſion of minds, be diſcourſed among you? I will not ſo much as name them, to give you cauſe to over-heat your ſelves to anſwer me; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to bury them, and all that you then ſaid about them: For I am no Spy upon you: I am a Gentleman; and if any other perſon that is an Informer may have taken notice of what you ſaid, and ſhould chance to call me to witneſs any thing againſt you, know I have a</hi> Gentleman's Memory, <hi>very apt to forget all upon ſuch an occaſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Diſcourſe (as I have been told) ſurpriſed them more than what was ſaid by the other <hi>Gentleman,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that the Company ſtared on him with ſilence, being moſt of them (I ſuppoſe) of Opinion, that what he ſaid was Reaſon: but as there is are all Companies ſome whom no Reaſon can ſatisfie, ſo there were (it ſeems) among them ſome few <hi>Emiſſaries, Trotters,</hi> and <hi>Miſchief-mongers</hi> belonging to the <hi>Canary Cabals,</hi> who began to grumble, but preſently broke up, and went to the ſeveral places of <hi>Caballing,</hi> and communicated the matter there to their Principals; among whom there hapning to be a <hi>falſe Brother,</hi> or two, by that means I got the Story.</p>
               <p>Now for a Concluſion:</p>
               <p>Let me anſwer one <hi>Objection</hi> which I hear walks about like a <hi>Bugbear</hi> to affright us. <hi>viz.</hi> That though our Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles tell us, that <hi>Edw. the Third</hi> conquer'd <hi>France,</hi> and his Son <hi>Edward,</hi> called the <hi>Black Prince,</hi> brought their
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41002:41"/>
King Priſoner into <hi>England:</hi> and though <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>5th.</hi> made a <hi>Second Conqueſt</hi> of them more compleatly, being Crowned King at <hi>Paris;</hi> and his Son <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> alſo Crowned there, and Reigned over them many years: yet the Caſe is alter'd now; <hi>France</hi> is quite another thing; it is now one compact Body; it in thoſe days was ſhared by diverſe <hi>Sovereign Princes,</hi> which made the <hi>French</hi> King but little in compariſon of what he is in theſe days; being become exceedingly more potent and more difficult to ſubdue, by reaſon of his preſent Lordſhip over all thoſe Sovereignties.</p>
               <p>To balance theſe Advantages of his, note, that <hi>England</hi> alſo is (through God's good Providence) become much more powerful than it was in thoſe days; For though in thoſe days we had <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet it was but a miſerable half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted Country, alwaies rebellious againſt us, ſo that it was an extraordinary charge and a clog rather than a help to us: but now we have it improved to the height, and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in good order with our <hi>Engliſh;</hi> alſo the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> a numerous and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like People, which then alſo was another great Clog up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, now united with us. To theſe Conſiderations add, That by addition of the Confederates, if they pleaſe to be plain with us, we may I ſuppoſe be contrepoiſe enough to anſwer all the <hi>French</hi> Advantages: and no Man that knows what <hi>England</hi> is at Sea, and what an <hi>Engliſh-Seaman</hi> is, will doubt, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>Holland</hi> joyn with us, that we may be a Match ſufficient for that King; and that we over-match him in this, that we have a <hi>Better Cauſe;</hi> and therefore (God pardoning our Iniquities in other matters) have a better hope of <hi>Divine Benediction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which being well weighd, we may very aptly invert the old Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Cicero, Juſtiſſimum Bellum iniquiſſimae Paci antefero.</hi> That is, being a little paraphraſed in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> I upon the whole matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude; <hi>That a moſt juſt War is to be preferred before a moſt unjuſt Peace, moſt dangerous to us, and all the reſt of the</hi> European <hi>Nations.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:41002:41"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
